<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The diuine eccho, or resounding voice from heauen moralized betwixt a Christian and his soule, with short and effectuall directions how to liue and die well. Whereby the effects of vertue and the defects of vice, mercy with miserie, heauenly felicitie with worldly vanity, the ioyes of heauen with the torments of hell, are familiarly expressed. Diuided into prayers and meditations for the ease and benefit of euerie Christian. The first part by Iohn Swift.</title>
            <title>Divine eccho, or resounding voice from heaven.</title>
            <author>Swift, John, fl. 1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 127 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3397</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1222:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The diuine eccho, or resounding voice from heauen moralized betwixt a Christian and his soule, with short and effectuall directions how to liue and die well. Whereby the effects of vertue and the defects of vice, mercy with miserie, heauenly felicitie with worldly vanity, the ioyes of heauen with the torments of hell, are familiarly expressed. Diuided into prayers and meditations for the ease and benefit of euerie Christian. The first part by Iohn Swift.</title>
                  <title>Divine eccho, or resounding voice from heaven.</title>
                  <author>Swift, John, fl. 1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[256] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for R. Bonion, and are to be sold at the shop in Paules Church-yard, at the Flower de Luce,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ (-A1) B-L¹²  M³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Diuine Eccho,</hi> OR, <hi>Reſounding voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, moralized betwixt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> and his ſoule, with ſhort and effectuall directions how to liue and die well. Whereby the effects of vertue and the defects of vice, mercy with miſerie, heauenly felicitie with worldly vanity, the ioyes of heauen with the torments of hell, are familiarly expreſſed. <hi>Diuided into Prayers and Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the eaſe and benefit of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Christian.</hi> The firſt part by <hi>Iohn Swift.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 27.9.</bibl>
               <p>My heart talked of thee O Lord, ſeeke ye my face:</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>R. Bonion,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the Flower de Luce. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull Sir EDMVND MORGAINE <hi>Knight, depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> Gouernour of the famous Towne of Garriſon of Porteſmouth, and the Ile of Porſee, and to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Maſter IOHN BRVEN Eſquire, my eſpeciall fauourers, all health and happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if your fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eyes may vout ſafe to read what my ſpare houres haue brought forth: thogh ſmal in ſhew, yet great in ſubſtance; I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly intreate you to be my protection; and thought it be but as a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:3397:3"/>ſtreame in reſpect of the whole Ocean of godly books that are gone before; yet therein when your leaſure beſt ſerues you, you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and comfort your ſelfe, vnto a farther backing on of your worſhips, godly, vertuos and religious liues.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.7</note> The word of God ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> is pure,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12</note> euen as ſiluer which from the earth is tried and purified ſeuen times in the fier, which word plainelie and plentifully telleth vs that iniquitie ſhall abound in the latter daies:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3.</note> how then ſhould I croſſe my lips, &amp; crie huſh, or peace, ſeeing that if Gods booke be true, while men cry peace, peace, ſudden deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:3397:3"/>ſhall fall vpon them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.30</note> The rather therefore I thought good to ſet foorth, to the view of the world, this my Diuine Eccho, whereby the godly may bee comforted and the wicked conuerted; I haue named it the Diuine Eccho, for that as your worſhips may ſee, how the Chriſtian ſoule doth ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly returne backe and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer like the Eccho, or rather I may ſay more truely like a voice from heauen, vnto what he demaundeth of her, directly giuing the laſt ſound of the word; both ſoule and body, heart and hand muſt agree together to ſerue the Lord. And if your worſhip
<pb facs="tcp:3397:4"/>ſhould aske me why I ſhould write thus phantaſtically (as you may terme it) of an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho, which before now was ſeldome or neuer heard of; I then muſt bring <hi>Dauid</hi> for my Author and pattern who in his 27. pſalme, when the Lord ſaid vnto him ſeeke yee my face, his ſoule anſwered like an Eccho, thy face Lord will I ſeek, ſeek my face, I ſeek thy face: and if you aske yet farther, why I ſhould bring in a ſecond or a Diuine <hi>Dyogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> it is to ſhewe how euerie man, and therefore much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how euery Chriſtian, ſhould liue contentedly with <hi>Dyogines</hi> the Cynicke, not caring for the thinges of this
<pb facs="tcp:3397:4"/>world, and vſing it, with <hi>Paul</hi> as if he vſed it not; Let mee now intreate your Worſhips grauities to accept hereof; as ſome token of my true and ſincere affection. And if this as I doubt not, bee entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with kinde acceptance, I purpoſe God willing heraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to preſent you with a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of better worth: ſo lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your Worſhips to the protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all Chriſtian dueties to be commaunded.</hi> Io. Swift.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:5"/>
            <head>The Epistletothe <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, I haue for thy good, ſet forth to thy view this my diuine Eccho, with godlie preparations to the practiſe of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; that ſo thou mayeſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditate, but alſo imitate, &amp; not onely prattle or talke thereon, but alſo practiſe it, the reward of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, with the ruine of vice, the ioyes of heauen, with the torments of hel, the world and its vanitie, with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and its felicity, alſo moſt ſweet comforts both diuine and morrall for all Chriſtians to increaſe their knowledge, in true godlines and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with a ſound caueat for ſinners, and wicked wretches, to haſten ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy repentance, whereby hels terror may be eſcaped, and the puniſhment due for ſinne, might likewiſe bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoided. <hi>Farwell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:5"/>
            <head>THE DIVINE <hi>ECCHO.</hi> Or ſhort and godly Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, betweene a ſecond or <hi>a Diuine</hi> DIOGENES and the Eccho, or a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and his Soule.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 1.</hi> A Prayer to God the Sonne the only Phiſition both of the ſoule and body.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Sweet Ieſus, thou doue-eyde lambe of God, ô ſweet Ieſus, the comforter of my ſoule; how amiable are thy lookes; O
<pb facs="tcp:3397:6"/>how beautiful thy countenance. O my ſole and ſoules delight, he that findeth thee, findeth all things, all that mans ſoule doth want, or that his hart can wiſh, and hee that looſeth thee, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all, for thou my loue art all in all; come then and refreſh my ſoule with thy lookes, for ſhee languiſheth and pines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away, becauſe thou doeſt not viſit her,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5.</note> ſhe is ſicke of loue and much grieues at thy long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: perhaps Lord becauſe ſhee hath many ſutors, thou thinkeſt that ſhee doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thee and thy company: its true my Lord, ſhe hath many indeed, but ſhee findes them falſe and diſſembling, ſhe likes them not, and will not marrie with any of them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>The.</hi> 5.21</note> but with thee onely with thee; ſhe hath tried all, and now ſhee keepes that
<pb facs="tcp:3397:6"/>which is beſt; diſdaine her not; though now ſhee bee troubled with an iſſue of teares, for the iſſue of her ſins, but rather come neere her, that ſhe may onely touch the hem of thy garment, and her iſſue ſhall bee dried vp; O then diſdaine her not. She hath touched vncleane thinges,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.25 <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.3.</note> whereby ſhe is become leprous and ſcabbed, O come then and touch her, and onely ſay, I wil, be thou cleane, and her leproſie ſhal be clenſed.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.7.</note> Nay ſhe is blind O Lord and can neither ſee nor yet conceiue thoſe things which are of thy ſpirit; O come and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint her eyes, waſh them in the poole &amp; fountaine of thy grace, and ſhee ſhall ſee againe. She is deafe and cannot heare, charme the charmer neuer ſo wiſely, come then and put thy fingers in her eares,<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> and crie but <hi>Ephphata</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3397:7"/>and they ſhall be opened, Shee is dumbe too and cannot ſpeak, ſhe cannot praiſe thy name, come then Lord cut that ſtring,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 7.32.</note> touch her tongue and ſhee ſhall openly glorifie thee, ſhe ſhall ſay and ſing with <hi>Mary, My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord and my ſpirit doth reioice in God my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.33. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 2.</hi> The blindneſſe and ignorance of the Atheiſt.</head>
               <p>YEt the Atheiſt not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this, vtterly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and neglecting my Lord, flies to nature; hee can tell thee that all things are thereby go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, but yet knowes not from whence nature her ſelfe is; the Sunne the Moone and Starres moue by nature: true it ſeemes
<pb facs="tcp:3397:7"/>to be, and true it may be, but moſt true wee know this to be, that God moues nature, all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and Starres are but his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 38. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.</note> Inſtruments to moue by mouing to effect, by effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to alter and order al things here below, heauen is his ſeate &amp; the earth his footſtoole, who when we runne awry ſpurns and kickes vs with the heele of his wrath, if then the loweſt and meaneſt part of his body (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and weakeſt too according vnto humane ſence) bee able to curb in our wandring appetites, what then me thinkes may his hands do, which alwaies holdes the bridle? tell mee my ſoule what may his hands doe, which haue made both heauen and earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4.24.</note> the ſea and land and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in both great and ſmall things. <hi>Ecch.</hi> All things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 3.</hi> A terror for Hypocrites and cold profeſſors.</head>
               <p>IF then there bee a God, why doe men ſtill hault betweene two opinions?<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.21.</note> ſaith <hi>Eliah:</hi> why are they creeples, and why walk they on crouches in their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: know they not, how that it is a long and hard way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and therefore a lame cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can neuer bee able to reach thither? if the Lord be God, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, but if <hi>Baal</hi> be he, then go after him: baule after <hi>Baal,</hi> for ſurely all lukewarme profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors the Lord will caſt and ſpew out of his mouth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut</hi> 22.</note> theſe Linſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wolſe mungrils glut and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the puritie of his ſtomack: is God then thinke ye, who is
<pb facs="tcp:3397:8"/>my ſweet Lord, my maker and my redeemer, like vnto <hi>Baal?</hi> or like <hi>Dauids</hi> Image? in his 135. Pſalme: one that hath eyes but cannot ſee their wickednes, one that hath eares yet cannot heare the crie of their ſinnes, One that hath a throat yet cannot roare after his pray,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 3.8.</note> one that is a ſleepe and vnderſtands not, or one that hath hands and cannot ſtrike? ſurely God is no Idol nor yet an idle God, but a liuing God, and if liuing, why then doth this age thinke him to be ſo patient as that hee will not reuenge his foes? or ſo weake, as that hee cannot, or ſo ignorant as that he knowes not how, or ſo fearefull as that he dares not? or elſe doe theſe wicked ones thinke him to be a lyer, who ſaith he will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh offences, and yet will not? He that ſaith there is no God is
<pb facs="tcp:3397:9"/>guiltie of damned Atheiſme, and he that thinkes in his heart, that there is a GOD, but withall thinkes him to be ſo patient and mercifull, as that hee will not reuenge in time to come, is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that horrible ſinne of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,<note place="margin">Pſalm. iſta.</note> and both fearefull, God is patient, and God is iuſt too, for mercy &amp; truth are met together, righteouſnes &amp; peace haue imbraced each other: his mercie is great we know, it is aboue all his workes, and wee finde it ſo,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.</note> for what ſaith my ſoule hath the Lord ſhewed himſelfe to bee, for that ſo long on our ſins hee hath euen winkt and ſmilde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Milde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 4.</hi> The careleſnes of the wicked in ſeruing God.</head>
               <p>MAny of the braue lads of this world are now tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gamſter, they thinke to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine Heauen by lot, if it bee their fortune to come in, well and good; ſo it is, alas poore fooles, if their chance be not the better, it may ſo chaunce, that they may all ſtand without at the doore with the fiue fooliſh Virgins and there pipe for colde and gnaſh their teeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.10 <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12.</note> with the fieri-frozen ſoules in hell; plaine caſting wil not win ſuch golden price, for if they know not how to help their die, they may there die without helpe, and yet neuer die; but pine in paine with the vnskilfull ſort, heauen is round I
<pb facs="tcp:3397:10"/>confeſſe yet not like Fortunes wheele, and he that thinkes with the former it is his fortune, if ſo be that hee comes thither, may chance if the ſpoakes of his wheele be not ſtronger, to lie in the mire, thus men play all their goods, yea &amp; their chiefeſt good too, at mum-chance, they ſtake their Soules at this vnfortunate game, and then if chaunce beare the ſway, the victory muſt needs bee doubtfull; but what wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would hazard ſuch a preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous price as his ſoule, at ſuch a baſe game, and with ſuch a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatching cogger as Sathan that grand-gamſter who can ſtrike a die at pleaſure? hee hath his falſe dice and al other ſhifts that may bee, to deceiue and blinde the eyes of our vnderſtanding, to winne the ſoules of poore do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting worldlings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 5.</hi> A Meditation on the birth of Chriſt, and the three wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens offerings,</head>
               <p>O Sweet Ieſus, O my ſweet, who art white and ruddy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Canti.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> O thou the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, when thou waſt borne there came wiſemen from the Eaſt euen the firſt fruite of the Gentiles to worſhip thee, and in their iourney they were guided by a Starre, which Starre did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them, brought them vnto thee vnto <hi>Bethlem,</hi> vnto that place where thou O prettie harmeleſſe ſmiling Babe didſt lye in a cratch: ſo graunt my Lord that thy word may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vaniſh from our eyes, that light of lights, that true light,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:11"/>but may bring vs to that place that heauenly <hi>Bethlem,</hi> which our ſoules moſt long after, euen as the Hart deſireth the water brookes, where wee ſhall ſee thee not as theſe wiſemen did, a ſeruant, but a Lord, not to bee iudged, but to iudge, not to call men to repentance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 21.27 <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.42 <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.15. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</note> but to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the vnrepentant, not ſitting on an Aſſe or ſtarueling beaſt, but riding on the ſtarrie skie, on the wings of the wind, not lying in a cold ſtable in a poor ragged manger, but in ſtate and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, in pompe and much glorie; And when theſe wiſemen had worſhipped, they opened their treaſures &amp; preſented vnto thee gifts, euen gold and incenſe and mirhe, and that becauſe Lord the Perſians manner was not to ſalute Kings without a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therfore that we neuer
<pb facs="tcp:3397:11"/>come vnto thee,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 93.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 99.1.</note> o thou the king of kings, vnleſſe we bring a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenttoo, euen an heart tried and purified as golde and ſiluer, an heart of incenſe and mirhe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout praiers, godlie Meditations that the ſauour thereof may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vp into the cloudes, and be a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice vnto thee, my loue, my hearts delight O thou the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 6.</hi> True knowledge what it is.</head>
               <p>MAny men in theſe daies, thinke themſelues wiſe becauſe they know and learne many things, though what they are bound to know, that they know not, that is to vnderſtand and learne the commandements of God, and theron to meditate
<pb facs="tcp:3397:12"/>day and night: they haue forgot that the wiſdome of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God; the knowledge of Gods lawes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth yong men ſober, for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall ſaith the prophet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</note> ſhall a young man clenſe his way? e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by ruling himſelfe after thy commandements: it doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort old men, it is wealth to the poore and treaſure to the rich, it feedeth the hungrie ſoules, it is a pleaſant riuer to the thirſtie heart, and it maketh al men wiſe and ſtill capeable of further knowledge, and ſurely hee that wanteth knowledge, or is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the wil of God, void of learning, and good education, howſoeuer then the world may make account of him, yet hee is but the ſhape of a man and no man, though neuer ſo wel beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with the outward giftes of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:12"/>nature, I ſay if he wanteth chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and godly nurture; he is but the gliding ſhape of a man and no man; Yet men are more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in keeping mens lawes, then in keeping of Gods, whereas thogh Gods laws yeeld the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and the greateſt reward that may be being kept, and the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them the greater yea &amp; the greateſt puniſhment of all. Not to perform what ſhould be done &amp; what is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, nay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by the mouth of god, doth betoken negligence, and to do what is forbidden is a ſign, if known, of preſumption, if not of ignorance, me thinkes I heare my ſoule anſwering me, how a man may offend God, as well as by committing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho</hi> Omitting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 7.</hi> The beſt knowledge is to knowe ones ſelfe.</head>
               <p>BEfore that a man can come to haue a true knowledge of any thing, he muſt firſt learne to know himſelfe, and hee that well knoweth himſelf, eſteemeth little of himſelfe, conſidering from whence he came, what hee is, and whither hee muſt, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth not the vaine pleaſures of this brittle life, but highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolleth the laws of God, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeketh to liue in his feare; but hee that knoweth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, is ignorant of Gods will, wilfull in ignorance, bold in wickedneſſe, moſt vnprofitable in his life, and vtterly graceles at the houre of his death. Learne thou then to know thy ſelfe for
<pb facs="tcp:3397:13"/>this is thy duty, &amp; he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that, which he ought to knowe, is a brute and ſenceleſſe beaſt amongſt men: and he that knoweth no more then he hath need of, is a man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt beaſts, but hee that delighteth in the knowledge of Gods wil, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out his works and wonders and thereby knoweth all that is fitting for a man to know, is a God amongſt men; Learn thou then to forget euill, for truely this is the beſt kinde of learning and not to knowe it is the ſureſt knowledge, in not learning it thou prooueſt thy ſelfe to bee a great Scholler euen a Doctor in Chriſts Schoole, &amp; in not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe to be the wiſeſt of all men: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art weake then thou art ſtrong,<note place="margin">Paulus ad cor.</note> when thou art ignorant then art thou expert.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 8.</hi> On good Councell what it is.</head>
               <p>IS not good councell better then gold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 7 8.</note> and more pretious then the Emerald, the Dyamond or Onyx ſtone? me thinkes it is, yet had men rather receiue gold and pearle and pretious ſtones then giue them, and can giue good Councell and will receiue none; this then is their follie, the fooliſh madnes of our time; yet diſpaire not, neither faint, for thou mayeſt thinke thy ſelfe a good Oratour if thou canſt onely perſwade others to do as they ſhould, though thou mayeſt thinke thy ſelfe a better when as thou canſt perſwade thy ſelfe to doe as thou oughteſt, but laſtlie thou mayeſt thinke thy ſelfe the chiefeſt of all, the beſt of all O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators
<pb facs="tcp:3397:14"/>elſe, when as thou canſt perſwade both thy ſelfe and alſo them, and ſo perſwade them that words may leaue ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit impreſſion in their hearts, ſo that thy bare and naked wordes may bee turned into ſound and perfit workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 9.</hi> A Meditation on Chriſt Ieſus borne in a Stable.</head>
               <p>OH that I had now a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares in each eye, that I might night and day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile and weepe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.12.</note> and bewaile the hard-heartedneſſe of the Iewes; oh my loue, what my loue borne in a ſtable? why, there might haue beene Beares and Wolues which might haue deuoured both thee &amp; thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too, there might haue been wilde horſes, that might haue
<pb facs="tcp:3397:15"/>kickt out thy braines, or Oxen that might haue trod vpon thee, &amp; ſo deſtroied thee? alas my loue what my loue and Lord both born in a ſtable? why the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſmell thereof might haue choaked, or the cold haue killed thee; ah hard-hearted Inne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, who did more reſpect royſting Ruffians, the braue lads of this world, then my Lord the Lord both of heauen and earth; yet more hard-hearted was thy wife, for me thinkes ſhe being a woman, ſhould haue weighed a womans caſe at ſuch a time, Oh that I had a ſtreame of teares ſtil guſhing out of mine eyes, that beholding heare the humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of God, I might bewaile the pride of men; But why ſhould I grieue and thus conceit my ſelfe of wilde-beaſts; ſeeing hee that was thy keeper was thy ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:3397:15"/>&amp; ſeeing he that kept thee doth neither ſlumber nor ſleepe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121</note> had it beene his wil that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not haue been borne there, thou ſhouldeſt not, it ſhould not haue beene done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 10.</hi> How the world is euen ſmothered vp with ſinne.</head>
               <p>OFtentimes as I haue ſtood on the high mountaine of Contemplation, yea euen a tipto on the top thereof, I haue much deſired that ſome others would haue likewiſe amounted vp thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto me to haue borne me company in theſe my ſolitarie ſtudies; ſo that there meditating they might turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from coaſt to coaſt, from quarter to quarter, from one part of the earth to another, and ſee how
<pb facs="tcp:3397:16"/>the world is beſmeared with the fat of ſinne, with abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and with all vncleaneſſe whatſoeuer; for I ſee how one in one part bragges and boaſtes in his bags, how another in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other quarter tryumpheth in his braueries, the third in his pelts, and another in his pots; but yet withal let the firſt know that his ſoule is ruſty,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10</note> and therefore hath that mightie one promiſed to ſcoure it in hel fier, if we wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue God &amp; his word, who wil not bee mocked; let the other know that his ſoule is puffed vp and ſwollen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 18.14</note> and therefore muſt it be preſſed downe, it is exalted and it muſt be brought lowe, let the third know that his ſoule is all filthy moſt beaſtly and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.8</note> and therefore without an earneſt repentance it will be caſt aſide into the ſtinking iakes of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:16"/>hell and damnation like to like,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15.</note> and let the laſt know how that hee hath glutted the Lord ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, how that the Lord hath ſurfeited with him and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his companions, and therefore ſhall in time to come, carouſe the cuppe of the Lords wrath and vengeance; oh that men then would once bee wiſe, &amp; not as the wiſeman ſpeaketh make but a ſport of ſinne: the foole ſaith pride is but a point of gentilitie, ſurfeiting ſparkes of good fellowſhip, beaſtly wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, trickes of youth, nay what ſaith he farther (my ſoule) is the effect of manhood and courage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Rage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 11.</hi> Sathans deceit to catch ſoules.</head>
               <p>SAthan that cunning fiſher, who knoweth in what holes the ſoules of men lie, hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented many baites to catch them, if hee cannot take them through pleaſure, hee baiteth beautie on his hooke, if not through beautie, honour, if not through honour riches, if not with riches ſome vanitie elſe, if one wil not ſerue, he vſeth ſome other meanes, ſo that if poſſibly he may, he will draw them into his net, vnleſſe they ſwim ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnder that rocke Chriſt Ieſus whereon the diuell is ſure to breake his tackling; ſo that by his ſuggeſtions one while wee burne in the heat of Deſire, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while we are rauiſhed with
<pb facs="tcp:3397:17"/>the thought of reuenge, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while inraged with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of dignitie, ſo that wee are neuer out owne vntill we leaue all, vntill wee leaue the world;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.8</note> And what though a man ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> liues many yeares, and in them all reioyce, yet hee muſt remember the daies of darkenes for they are many: well then let men like reſty Iades take the bit in their mouthes at libertie, let them refreſh their ſoules with vanities, let them delight in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, let them poſſeſſe heaps of riches, let them liue pleaſantly let them fare daintily, let them drinke luſtilie, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lodge ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; but yet withall let them know that God at length will curbe them in; that they muſt al appeare before the iudgement ſeate of his Maieſtie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> remember then thy creator in the dayes of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:18"/>thy youth, for all this is but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; if <hi>Salomon</hi> had beene a foole, who was the wiſeſt of all men, thou mighteſt then haue accuſed him of follie; or if <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> had not taſted theſe vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (who taſted them al to their full) thou mighteſt then haue condemned him of ignorance, in not knowing their ſwetneſſe; if then thou canſt neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue his wiſdome, nor yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, why wilt thou not yeeld that all is vanity?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 12.</hi> A Meditation on Chriſt who is the true light.</head>
               <p>O Thou bright morning ſtar oh thou bright morning Sunne, and ſonne of God, by thine ariſing wee wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:3397:18"/>Prognoſticate that the threatning clouds of thy fathers anger ſhall flee away, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall bee cleare and calme, the ayre ſweet and wholſome if ſo be that wee beleeue in thee and deſire to be lightned by thy word,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 105.</note> for thy word O Lord is a Lanthorne vnto my feete and a light vnto my pathes; Thou haſt giuen vs this world for a walke and thy word for a guide, ſo that wee may eaſily without ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and falling recouer the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of our iourney, recouer our iourneys end, for when thy word goeth forth ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> it giueth light &amp; vnderſtanding euen vnto the ſimple, this is that light the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby we muſt walk, this is that light which muſt guide our feete, and vnleſſe we walke by this light, wee may ſoone fall into confuſion, for
<pb facs="tcp:3397:19"/>heere in one place lieth whole quagmires of ſinne, in another blockes of error and ignorance, in the third the ſlipperie yee of deceitfull vanities of vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and without thy light O Chriſt (who art the true light) and the light of thy word and Goſpell, we may ſoone ſticke in theſe quagmires, we may ſoon ſlide and fall downe on this yee; Direct then O Lord our pathes that wee fall not, who art the true light and lampe of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 13.</hi> The vanitie of worldly things.</head>
               <p>DAme Nature, yea one bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then nature, euen God himſelfe, hath put a diuiſion betweene man and beaſte, yet
<pb facs="tcp:3397:19"/>man by all meanes ſtriues to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a baaſt, to damme vp the courſe of nature, nay, rather to croſſe the wil of God, and is not this ſtrange, that men ſhould be ſo ſwiniſh; ſtrange it is indeed, yet not ſo ſtrange as true; when as they liue and dy in ſenſuality. Men while they liue here in this tranſitorie world, ſhould ſo delight in the book of God, that they may leaue the name of a good man, I meane the name of a good Chriſtian behinde them when they are dead; and if wee leaue that it is all we can leaue, nay, it is the greateſt of all other things that may be left behinde: and no man wil, no man can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect more at our hands; but he that doth not leaue this behind him when he is dead, carrying it about with him while hee is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, ſurly is no man, but a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:3397:20"/>whoſe eſtate is farre worſe then the dogges, the toades, or any other filthy creature: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Catalogue of the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fooles, the follie of one haue I moſte deepely ſounded; let him therefore beare home the bell, &amp; that is he who name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemes the world, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeth no man, and maketh no reckoning of GOD, who ſo greatly regardeth all men, what folly can bee greater then this, ſeeing that the world is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an hoſteſſe with whom when a poore trauailer hath ſpent all the money in his purſe, ſhe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth him out of her doores, and there with all telling him, that ſhee is wearie of ſuch trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, ſo when a man hath ſpent all time ſo pretious heere in this world, he muſt at laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of it, hee muſt away, hee
<pb facs="tcp:3397:20"/>muſt vaniſh, &amp; for that he here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore did not forſake the world the world wil now forſake him; &amp; what thinkeſt thou, my ſoule, will the world doe at length by flattering vs now with delights, and with pleaſures by feaſting vs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Sting vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 14.</hi> The miſerable estate of the volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous worldling.</head>
               <p>TRue it is, that when a man, doth not bridle his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they carrie him headlong vnto all licentious liuing, which cauſeth him to iudge not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto reaſon, but according vnto ſence, and where men haue ſuch a libertie to offend, how ſweet is ſinne vnto the fleſh? ſo that there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb facs="tcp:3397:21"/>men and beaſts, ſaue that men do exceed beaſts in beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſenſualitie: oftentimes as I haue breathed, I haue thought with my ſelfe, what could be moſt like vnto mans breath, and nothing could I finde ſo fit to be compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as pleaſure, as pleaſing beaſtlineſſe, which vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſo ſoone as it is ſeene. I would then that men would cheare vp, their lowring melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholike ſpirits, with the ſweete harmony of the Goſpell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and awaken their drowſie ſoules with the alarum of reſolution vnto Godlineſſe, for they muſt knowe that there is no greater ſhame, then for a man to bee reſolute in worldlie actions, &amp; yet wauering doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the chiefe points of their ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 15.</hi> To bee conſtant in the Lords ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: and examples thereof.</head>
               <p>SVrely <hi>Paul</hi> was conſtant, yea and reſolute too, in the points of his ſaluation: for he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and ſtirre vp others,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note> to doe the like, fight the good fight of faith ſaith he: O noble Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier! O famous conquerer! mee thinkes no man ſhould refuſe to drawe the ſword of the ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt his moſt deadly enemies the world, the fleſh and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, and ſeeing that againſt theſe three tyrannicall perſecutors, al thoſe that would bee accounted good Chriſtians dayly warre ſo long as they are in their earthlie Tabernacles, they know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that they haue a good Captaine euen Chriſt Ieſus, who
<pb facs="tcp:3397:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>will giue them their full pay, ſo that they ſhall looſe nothing by their fight,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> and out of <hi>Bethleem</hi> came this Captaine to gouerne his people Iſrael. All the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Martyrs and holy Saintes of God be his Lieutenants, who follow their captain Chriſt cloſe at the heeles, and will not ſhrink one iot from him, who in ſteade of a feather hung and bedeckt with golden aglets had a crown of thornes vpon his head, beſet round about with prickles, and Lieuetenant <hi>Paul,</hi> Lieuetenant <hi>Peter</hi> and al the reſt of his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants in generall; in ſtead of honour had diſhonour, in ſteed of mirth, mourning, in ſteed of reuerence, reuilings, and in ſteed of being made much of, they were made roockes of; Now the flag or ancient which the Godly beare into the fieldes, and in
<pb facs="tcp:3397:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>which they tryumph and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce is the Croſſe of Chriſt, whence ſaith one Auncient-bearer amongſt the reſt, <hi>abſit,</hi> God forbid that I ſhould reioice in any thing, but in the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</note> whereby the world is crucified vnto mee and I vnto the world;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.</note> our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines colours are the red croſſe in a white field, white and red, white in reſpect of his innocent pureneſſe or pure innocencie, red in reſpect of his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when drops of bloud iſſued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; came trickling down his cheeks: who koweth not then my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued, my welbelooued is white and ruddy, the chiefeſt of ten thouſands; the drummers and Trumpeters of this armie are the Miniſters of Gods word, who lift vp:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſai.</hi> 85.</note> their voices like trumpets to ſhew Gods people
<pb facs="tcp:3397:23"/>their ſinnes, and the houſe of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acob</hi> their tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter downe the wals of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Ierico: the common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of this band are al the elect and faithfull ſeruants of God in generall; laſtly the place where this Captain, theſe Lieutenants, theſe Ancient-bearers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant</hi> 5.1.</note> theſe Drummers, Trumpiters, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers, doe march and meete together is the church of God, there wee muſt keepe our randeuow, there we muſt eate &amp; drink, &amp; make our ſelues merry, there muſt be our court of gard, for ſaith our Captaine, where two or three are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.</note> there am I in the midſt of them, there, there doth he teach vs how to fight, there, there doth he traine vs vp; there doth he place vs in battell rew, and teach vs how to put on
<pb facs="tcp:3397:23"/>the breſtplate of righteouſneſſe, the ſword of the ſpirit, and the hope of ſaluation for an helmet; O let vs not ſuffer then our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to ruſt, for if it ruſt, our Captaine and Sauiour, Ieſus Chriſt, when hee ſhall come at that great day of muſter, at the day of iudgement, when as all ſoules ſhall be muſtered vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he will thinke vs to bee but idle and ſlouthfull ſeruants; O therefore come fellow ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, let vs march on ſtill, ſtand your ground, yeelde not the bucklers, be reſolute and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, for wee haue receiued preſſe-money in our baptiſme, there, there haue wee vowed to be the ſouldiers of Chriſt; ſtand to it then ſtoutly, yeeld not vnto the vaine pleaſures of the world; come I ſay let vs march on; for heare yee not how the holy
<pb facs="tcp:3397:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ghoſt ſoundeth out the drum of comfort, of triumph, of ioy, of peace, and all happineſſe; cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Be thou faithfull vnto the death, and I will giue thee a crowne of life, and heare ye not the merrie ſluit and pipe, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt ſweetly and ſinging in the ayre.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.10</note> To him that ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth will I grant to ſit with me in my kingdome.</p>
               <p>o.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 1.</hi> A meditation on Chriſts riding to Ieruſalem on an aſſe.</head>
               <p>O Bountifull Ieſus, whoſe head is as fine gold, whoſe lockes are curled,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant</hi> 5.11. <hi>Math.</hi> 21.7</note> and blacke as a rauen, thou entredſt Ieruſalem fitting on an aſſe. O low and humble minde of ſo great a king! thou waſt poore too ſweet Lord when thou entredſt in the
<pb facs="tcp:3397:24"/>citie, for thou borrowedſt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to couer thine harmeles bodie; though thou waſt owner of all, both in heauen and earth, thou waſt poore indeed, for thou haddeſt not whereon, or wherein to reſt thine head, thou waſt borne poore, thou liuedſt poore, and thou diedſt poore, poore &amp; naked, here me thinks my Lord doth condemne our pride, and the pride of thoſe that were heirs of <hi>Dauids</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to ſee how magnifically in what pompe and ſtate, with how many vaine glorious plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits of the people, and riding in Chariots al glittering with gold, they entred in that citie Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and to ſee now, how my Lord rideth in vpon an aſſe, without any furniture, onely his diſciples thread-bare coates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt vpon her. And what is
<pb facs="tcp:3397:25"/>my Lord indeed rode before in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e? well then I will lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie after, let vs make haſte vnto the gates of the citie, and there knocke while they may be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs: Let vs run a pace, I ſay, leaſt that wee bee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the fooliſh virgins, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite enim, neſcio vos, Goe away for I know you not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 17.</hi> How a man muſt be conſidered.</head>
               <p>IN what ſtate things temporal and tranſitorie ſtand, euen in the ſame doth man;<note place="margin">Senccae E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 77.</note> that ſhip is called good and fortunate, not ſhe which is painted out with pretious colours, nor ſhe whoſe ancor is made either of gold or ſiluer, or whoſe cable is made of fine twiſted-ſilke, nor yet ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:3397:25"/>that is fraught with a princes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes, nor yet with the whole wealth of a kingdome; but ſhe that is ſtable and firme, whoſe ioynts are cloſe and found, ſwift in her iourney, and long liuing on the ſeas foming waues; that ſword is called good, not that whoſe hilts are gilded, or whoſe ſheath is beſet with pearles, but that ſword, which hath a ſharpe and well ſeaſoned edge, able to cut whatſoeuer it ſhall bee put vnto; the carpenter commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not his rule for the beautie thereof, but for the true meaſure and ſtreightneſſe of it, and in man it auaileth nothing, how many acres of ground he plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, how many he foweth, how much money hee puts ſorth to vſe, of how many hee is ſaluted and called maſter, how ſoft the bed be that he lies in, or how
<pb facs="tcp:3397:26"/>pretious the cuppe bee that hee drinkes in, and the like; but how good and vertuous he be; how ſharpe the edge of his zeale is to cut downe ſinne, and how ſtreight his feete walke in the wayes of the Lord; We ſee then that whoſoeuer is a mightie man, is not therby a good man, but he that is good is thereby a mightie man, yea and preſently mightie, as heat is vnſeparable from fire, ſo is might from goodnes; none of theſe whom riches onely raiſe to honour, are to be called great men, why then do we cal them great? a dwarffe if thou ſhalt meaſure his baſis or foundation, will not prooue a tall man, though hee ſtand on a mountaine, and a Church pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar wil keepe its height though it ſtand in a pit-hole; and this is our faults, for that we neuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme
<pb facs="tcp:3397:26"/>a man as he is, but wee ad vnto him tranſitorie and our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, but if then thou wilt truely conſider the worth, and worthines of a man, behold him bare and naked, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the good parts and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 18.</hi> The praiſe of vertue.</head>
               <p>OFrentimes haue I ſeene fooles, yea and vicious liuers too, to get many ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with cap &amp; knee, but what may they thank for it, their weed not their wit, their garments and not their deſerts, their veſtures &amp; not their vertues, yet howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he be deſcended, I am ſure, that hee boaſteth in vaine of his great linage and parentage; that
<pb facs="tcp:3397:27"/>hauing no good qualitie in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felſe, ſeeketh to be eſteemed for the Nobilitie of his aunceſtours, There is nothing on earth more like to God then a man perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vertuous, who doth ſo much excell others, as GOD excels him; &amp; as far as the minde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes the body in dignitie, ſo farre doth he that is a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his deſerts and good quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties exceed the other, that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led maiſter onely through his many Lands and Lordſhips.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 19.</hi> For what men are eſteemed in theſe daies.</head>
               <p>BVt now the world is come to ſuch an vntowardneſſe that <hi>an Dines ſit omnes quarimus nemo an bonus,</hi> we all aske whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3397:27"/>ſuch a man bee rich or no; no man asketh whether he bee godly and vertuous, neither doe we demaund or inquire how he came by his riches, but how much hee hath, and as his goods increaſe ſo is he eſteemed, if a man bee rich and therewithall bountifull, though neuer ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, wee account him a good honeſt man, God ſaue his life, ſay we, thus riches are a band to all villany, a rich man may as ſoone be acquitted as play the knaue, the Humble Bee breakes throgh the Cob-webbe, when as the poore ſillie Flie is catched, and it is a thing worthy of note to ſee how men flocke to the place of execution, and thrung together to ſee an offender looſe his life, or ſome naughtie packe carted; Strange it is indeed, and I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereat, and worth the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:3397:28"/>if they may be noted, when as ſome of theſe lookers on, haue ſtolne twice as much, and hath murdered twiſe as many as hee hath that is executed; and again when as ſome of theſe gazers haue plaied the ſtrumpet fiue times for her once, that is now puniſhed, and thus tormented by the decree of the Law: yet if he that dyeth for his offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath ſtoln thrice as much as thou haſt and in the meane ſpace thou art not ſeene, or beeing ſeene art winked on, or rather nodded at, tell mee which of you two, may challenge the degree happinſſe? ſurely me thinkes that friend which laboureth to caſe vp any heinous fact in a guiltie perſon, knowes not what he doeth, for the one is the Butcher, and the other the knife, and both ſeeke to rippe vp the bowels of their
<pb facs="tcp:3397:28"/>own ſoules, without the greater grace of God, and greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: the butcher is the murderer, and therefore to be condemned, the knife is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of murder, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be contemned, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is a third partie to be arraigned at the barre of Gods Iuſtice, and that is the Iudge, when the faultie is freed, when the guiltie is acquitted, for tell me my ſoule, how are moſt of thoſe malefactors hearts, after that by the vniuſt bribe-taking Iudge, they are openly pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Hardoned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 20.</hi> A Meditation on Chriſts going vnto the mount of Oliues.</head>
               <p>OMerciſull Ieſus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cantic.</hi> 5.</note> Oh ſweet Chriſt, my loue, my doue my deare, whoſe eyes are like doues vppon the riuers of the waters, which are waſht with milke and remaine by the full veſſels: hee is dou-eyde indeed truely dou-eyde, hee is like vnto <hi>Noahs</hi> doue,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Genſ.</hi> 8.10.</note> which <hi>Noah</hi> when as the Deluge was ouer all the world, ſent forth our of the Ark, and the doue came to him in the euening, and loe in her mouth was an Oliue leaf which ſhe had pluckt, wherby <hi>Noah</hi> knew that the waters were abated from off the earth: And when the world was drowned with ſinne God the father ſent foorth from the Arke of heauen his Sonne
<pb facs="tcp:3397:29"/>Chriſt, which prettie harmeleſſe doue returned with an oliue branch in his mouth too, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may all know that the waues of Gods wrath are aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from off the earth, for in this doue he was well pleaſed, this was he in whom he delighted: againe we read in the Goſpell that this innocent doue,<note place="margin">Iohn.</note> came vnto the mount of Oliues,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.1.</note> when as he was about, by his death to ſaue our ſoules, the ſoules of men, he came thither; Firſt, to the mount of Oliues, for hee came to make peace betweene God &amp; man, and the Oliue tree doth betoken peace, it is the character of peace, as the Oliue branch in the pigeous mouth, and Chriſt hath brought this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue into the world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14.</note> for he is our peace, which hath made both one, and hath broken downe
<pb facs="tcp:3397:30"/>the ſtop of the partition-wall; As in old time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omeſ.</hi> 8.9.</note> before that the floods were diminiſhed from off the earth, the doue had not whereon to reſt the ſoles of her feet, and we before that the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtreames of Gods wrath were gone (through Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits) from off the world, had not likewife wheron to reſt the feet of our ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 21.</hi> Good and bad muſt not bee mixt together.</head>
               <p>MAny men there are who haue libertie, in their liues, &amp; what may be the cauſe of this but want of grace? ſome againe there are who haue liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in their hands, and this is a ſigne of theft, ſome alſo haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie
<pb facs="tcp:3397:30"/>in their tongues, and this betokens folly; and many again there be, who haue libertie in their mindes, and this warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth their goodneſſe, and no man liueth truely at libertie, but he that liueth godly, who ſo is vertuous, who ſo is freed from the bondage of ſin; learne thou then not onely to liue, but to know how to liue, for the firſt of theſe each beaſt doth couet, but the latter becommeth a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; ſeeke then to purifie thy ſoule in the fountaine of grace, thy ſoule and heart both muſt be cleſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.</note> for ſuch as the tree is ſuch is the fruit; a good tree, ſaith Chriſt, cannot bring forth bad fruit, neither can a bad tree bring forth good fruit: art thou a bad man, and doth a good ſentence proceed from thy mouth, ſurely thou diſgraceſt the ſentence, for
<pb facs="tcp:3397:31"/>we knowe that thou art but a Crab-tree ſtocke, and therefore thy fruit muſt needs relliſh verie ſower, art thou a good man, and doth bad words and come out of thy lippes? thou makeſt thy words not the better, but thy ſelfe the worſe, thy filthy words are as fruite that is blited, this maketh men to curſe the ſtocke though thou in thy ſelfe mayeſt come of the right kinde, in any caſe ſuffer not what is good to be mingled with what is naught for a bad word will ſooner diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace a good man, then a good man can grace what wee know to be bad, what is good may be ſtained with what is naught, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which is naught may be made good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 22.</hi> A Meditation on the loſſe of Chriſt when hee was but twelue yeares old.</head>
               <p>COmfort my ſoule oh Lord, ſtretch foorth thine hands of compaſſion, and reach vnto me euer laſting life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.</note> whoſe hands are as rings of Gold, ſet with the cryſolite, whoſe bellie like white Iuorie couered with Saphirs; whom <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſought ſorrowing, but could not finde him vntill the third day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> they ſought my Lord in the Citie, and in the Countrie, within the wals, and without the wals, in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem and abroad among his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, but could not finde him, and they ſorrowed the more for that they loſt their Sonne, when as he was but twelue yeares old:
<pb facs="tcp:3397:32"/>O ſweet childe, where waſt? where didſt hide thy ſelfe? who gaue thee houſe-roome? who gaue thee meate and drink? who pluckt off thy hozen and ſhun?<note place="margin">De omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inquit Bernard: Coniicere vel opinari aliquid li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, affirma re autem temere non licet. Mark <hi>10</hi>
                  </note> who made cleane thy coates? what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany diddeſt thou vſe? whether in heauen or earth, or in any houſe in the meane time didſt thou remaine? ſurely thou waſt in ſome ſecret place, with ſome of thy yong and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeares, teaching them the ſecrets of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, according to thine owne words in the Goſpell: ſuffer lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Children to come vnto mee, and forbid them not, but what was the cauſe my ſweet Lord, that thou haddeſt no compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on thy poore mother ſeeking thee, grieuing for thee, ſighing and ſobbing and powring out whole ſtreams of teares for loſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3397:32"/>of thee; And why <hi>Mary</hi> diddeſt thou ſeeke the child ſo earneſtly whom thou kneweſt to be God directly; diddeſt thou feare leaſt that he was ſtarued with hunger or vexed with cold, or leaſt that he ſhould be wronged by ſome Children playing in the ſtreetes? what is not this hee who defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all men, who feedeth all things, who nouriſheth all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures liuing, who doth array and cloath the graſſe of the fielde, which groweth now and a non is caſt into the ouen, and makes them more glorious, then Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in all his royalties?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 23.</hi> On the ſame.</head>
               <p>WEe ſee here with what ſighing and ſobbing, with what lamenting, with how great ſorrowing, grieuing and
<pb facs="tcp:3397:33"/>groaning they ſought the babe, and ſpecially <hi>Mary</hi> his mother; and how great this was who is able to expreſſe? euery word ſhe ſpoake was ſhut vp with a teare, teares made full ſtops yet were her wordes neuer fully ended, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie line ſhe vttered had a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis with wringing and wrefling of the handes, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as <hi>Ruben</hi> did, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſought his brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.30</note> and could not finde him. The Childe is not heere, and I, whether ſhall I go? and <hi>Mary</hi> when ſhe ſought her ſonne and could not finde him, cried likewiſe the childe is not heere, and I, whither ſhall I goe? the childe is not heere, oh the childe is not here, and I whither ſhall I goe? and wee therefore, who haue loſt this childe <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> this babe Chriſt; through ſinne, muſt ſeeke him againe by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:33"/>with much grieuing and ſorrowing as <hi>Mary</hi> did, if we cannot finde him in one prayer, we muſt goe vnto another, and neuer ceaſe crying with <hi>Rubin,</hi> and I whither ſhall I goe?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 24.</hi> On death, how it is our greateſt friend.</head>
               <p>IT is the manner and faſhion of men in this age, to ſalute thoſe whome they meet, to ſalute and imbrace all their friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; yet is there one whome we dayly meet, and our greateſt friend too, but we take no notice of him, death I meane who is our friend, yea and our chiefeſt friend, for by him wee paſſe ouer the ſeas of miſery, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bleſſed land of reſt and true felicitie, we meet him daily, yet we thinke not on him, the
<pb facs="tcp:3397:34"/>longer we liue the more inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly wee are acquainted together, and the nearer wee come vnto him:<note place="margin">Hieronimus</note> 
                  <hi>quotidie morimur</hi> ſaith one father, <hi>&amp; quotidie commutamur,</hi> we die dayly and we are daily &amp; hourely changed, yet are our ſoules immortall, and heereon hangs the Chriſtians ioy: death then is ſuch a friend that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which the godly cannot liue, for it is <hi>tranſitus</hi> a paſſage vnto life euerlaſting, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on do the Godly Meditate both night and day;<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> and without the which the wicked muſt not liue, it keepes downe their proude hearts, it keepes them in awe, &amp; ſeruill feare, for if it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they would euen ſcorne God to his face, and bid him do what he durſt doe; if the godlie be deſirous to liue, it is a token that they are bent to doe ſome
<pb facs="tcp:3397:34"/>good, but on the contrarie, if the wicked would liue it is to doe ſome miſchiefe; yet in the end neither good nor bad can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand death; ſome die at firſt, ſome at laſt, ſo that all die at length: death ſurely to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded man is life, whoſe meditation is on diuine matters, and whoſe hope is the ioyes of heauen, none indeed doe feare death, ſaue thoſe that haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo much iniquity, as after death deſerueth damnation: for hell is reſerued of old for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, but where are the godly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.</note> what ſaith thy ſoule <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> In eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 25.</hi> On the ſuddenneſſe thereof and vncertaintie.</head>
               <p>THe world ſaith that a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie heart liues long, but I ſay a ioyfull ſoule liues for euer, it is not the death that deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſoule but a bad life; therefore God hath hid the time of our departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſhould make haſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, for if wee now knowing how that death comes ſuddenly are careleſſe of Gods ſeruice, what would wee doe if wee did know it to bee delayed for ſome long time:<note place="margin">Auguſt. in libr. de Scrip. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet vltimus dies, vt obſeruentur omnes dies,</hi> our laſt day is not knowne vnto vs, becauſe wee ſhould ſtill be ſo prepared, as if the next day ſtill following were the appointed time of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:35"/>we ſee if a man looſe a thing of any price,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15.8.</note> he will ſeeke for it foote after foote: yea and light a candle too, as the goſpell ſpeaketh, whereby he may bee aſſured not to ouerſlip what hee loſt. So we if we meane to finde heauen, muſt begge of God by earneſt prayer, to illighten our feete with the lampe of his holy ſpirit, and ſo make conſcience of all our waies, and examine eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtep, vntill wee haue found what we ſought, a thing of great praiſe and priſe: be ſure then to ſtep charily, for O man ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> it is cetaine that thou muſt die, but vncertaine where, how or when. Becauſe then that death doth looke for thee, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie place and at all times, doe thou then alſo if thou art wiſe, look for it euerie where too, and this me thinkes is the beſt way
<pb facs="tcp:3397:36"/>to match ſubtill death. But men in theſe daies who haue not this knowledge, doe moſt ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complaine vpon God for the ſhortneſſe of their liues, when as they as ſhort as it is, doe throgh ryoting, ſurfeiting, drinking, and bowſing, and through malice &amp; murders, make it more ſhort both in themſelues, and alſo in others, yet mee thinkes if men would duely conſider, of what molde they are made, they wold not be ſo careleſſe of their ſoules health, and of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, one ſillie flea in the night will ſoone breake their ſleepe, one ſmall pricke with a thorn or pin, will euen force teares to iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue from their eyes: if thy body were braſſe or ſteele, then O man thou mighteſt haue ſome cauſe to tryumph and glorie in thy ſelfe, thou mighteſt haue
<pb facs="tcp:3397:36"/>ſome cauſe to think thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſiſt all misfortune, and to withſtand all putrifaction, but marke I pray thee the frailtie of thy fleſh, which if it lie in the graue but onely three or foure daies, thy dereſt friend that thou leaueſt behinde thee, will not be able by reaſon of the noyſome ſmell of thy dead carkaſſe to come neere it, or yet once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſight thereof: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber now that thou art but duſt and wormes meate, and beare therefore about thee the Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of thy faults, ſearch into the botome of euery particular fin, and goe into the houſe of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and not into the houſe of feaſting, for where ſorrowing for ſinnes and ſadneſſe is, there is the heart of wiſemen, but where mirth is, there is the heart of fooles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 26.</hi> The frailtie of our bodies.</head>
               <p>MAny times haue I thought with my ſelfe, how that it may one day ſo come to paſſe, that this earthly bodie of ours, now pampered vp, &amp; kept from the winde and weather, now ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noured &amp; much reſpected, may one day ſerue to make vp a mud-wall: for a time may happen, when ſome building may bee made neare vnto the graue (bee it neuer ſo gay and ſumptuous) and that they might digge for ſome earth out of the ſame to make morter for a wall,<note place="margin">Omnes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimur et ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut aqua labimur, in terram. Eccl.</note> and ſo ſhall thy feely bodie, being now changed into earth, become af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards an earthen wall: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be at this preſent, the moſt noble body (and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licately
<pb facs="tcp:3397:37"/>cheriſhed) of all bodies in the world; and how many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Kings and Emperours (I wonder) haue come already to theſe promotions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho</hi> Ocyons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 27.</hi> On the ſame.</head>
               <p>O The baſeneſſe and beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bodie, when as the ſoule is departed out of it, and O the continuall moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and waſting of our life, and haſtning vnto this baſenes; what minute of an houre paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth but that we go one ſtep for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards our death? what other thing thinke ye is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Heauens, but as it were a very ſwift wheele, which is continually ſpinning and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:3397:38"/>vp our liues, for like as a rolle of wooll, ſaith one father, is ſpunne vpon a wheele, of the which, at euerie turning about, ſome part is wound vp, at the firſt turne a little, at the ſecond a little more, and ſo forth at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie turne vntill all be ended: ſo doth the wheele of the heauens continually ſpinne and windc vp our life, in that at euerie turning round that it maketh a peece of our life is ſpunne and wound vp; and therfore holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.25.</note> that his daies were more ſwift then one that rideth in poſte: for hee that rideth in poſt, though his meſſage requireth neuer ſo much haſte, yet ſometimes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie cauſeth him to ſtay: but our life neuer ſtaieth, neither wil it giue vs ſo much libertie, as the ſpace of one houre of reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 28.</hi> Why God will not haue vs to haue knowledge of things to come.</head>
               <p>IN this, as in all other things the wiſdome of God is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, who will not haue, nor yet ſuffer men to haue knowledge of future things, of things to come, for if they had apreſcience or foreknowledge of their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie they would bee careles and negligent toward God their maker, and againe vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their aduerſitie, they wold be ſenceles, as a male-fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who commonly is halfe dead, ſo ſoone as the rope is caſt about his necke; man therefore hath only knowledge of things preſent and paſt, of things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for that he may at all times
<pb facs="tcp:3397:39"/>behold the workes of God and preſently betake himſelfe vnto a new and holy life, vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly meditations; oft paſt, for that he may giue God glory for his good deedes,<note place="margin">Iames.</note> ſeeling that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good &amp; perfect gift com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from aboue, and be ſorie for his bad, his corrupt and euill life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 29.</hi> What a good conſcience is, and the praiſe thereof.</head>
               <p>THe beſt way for a man, to promiſe his ſoule euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, after death, is to make much of a good conſcience while he liues; ſurely the wiſeſt of kings, king <hi>Solomon</hi> had tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly taſted the delicacie of this daintie diſh, in that he calleth it
<pb facs="tcp:3397:39"/>a continuall feaſt, a meat wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he could neuer be glutted: by it the innocent ſmileth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the furiouſnes of the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful iudge, when as in the meane ſpace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 15.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.22.</note> the guiltie by inward gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings diſcouereth his offence, though all men ſeeme to winke at it, nay before he be ſuſpected of any: It is a bad conſcience that purſues his maſter at the heeles, and knoweth how to take vengeance in due time, hee will not ceaſe to poſt after him, vntill hee hath pind him to the bar, for let him be girded about with Iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, garded with ſouldiers, attended on by counſellers, ſhut vp with wals of braſſe, in ſtrong holds and caſtles, yet will he be in a woefull caſe, in a perplexed miſery, ſeeing that there is no ſalue for a ſicke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience; ſurely it is like vnto thoſe mice which
<pb facs="tcp:3397:40"/>deuoured one <hi>Hatto</hi> a merciles biſhop of Germanie,<note place="margin">Munſter in Coſmo.</note> for if hee ſaile out vpon the ſeas, it will ſwimme after the ſhip, yea and be readie to drowne the puppe, if he place himſelfe in the center of a fietie circle, it will leape o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto him, if hee aſcend vp vnto the top of a caſtle it will climbe vp vnto him by the wals, if hee deſcend downe into the earth, it will dig him vp againe, if he ſleepeth he ſhall haue feare for his bedfellow, if he awaketh &amp; walketh abroad, he ſhal haue care for his companion, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the ſting of conſcience for his torment, there is no way to preuent it but by death, and this alſo is vncertaine, which maketh it the more grieuous, for ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſhall bee preſently hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or more grieuouſly hated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 30.</hi> We muſt make ſpeed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</head>
               <p>THerefore when thou goeſt from home ponder with thy ſelfe, what thou wilt doe abroade, and when thou retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt home, call to minde what thou haſt done there, when thou ariſeſt in the morning, determin to paſſe the day following, as if at night they bed ſhould be thy graue, and when thou lyeſt downe ſo commit &amp; commend thy ſpirit to God the father that thou mayeſt ariſe with his ſonne Chriſt, then care not ſo much for the health and welfare of thy body, that thereby thou mayeſt haue a long life heare on earth, as for the ſafety of the ſoule, how thou mayeſt liue for euer. Me
<pb facs="tcp:3397:41"/>thinkes I ſee time ſit laughing, and why? for that ſhe runneth ſwiftly, and mocketh men for their ſlowneſſe, for ſlacking their duetie towards God: our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe is, hee that is before hand need not run, be not thou ſlow then in thy repentance; behold thy face in Gods Bible, that cleare looking-glaſſe &amp; if thou appeareſt faire and beautifull do ſuch things as becom thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but if thou ſeemeſt fowle, full of ſpots and ilfauoured, then ſtudy to attaine vnto that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie or comelineſſe which thy face lacketh; labour diligently to correct thoſe deformed blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that are ſeene in thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 31.</hi> On flatterers and diſſemblers.</head>
               <p>WE ought to beware of thoſe praiſes which proceed out of the mouthes of wicked men, when as their hearts are moſt inſyncere and diſſembling: for we our ſelues know this, that when we would kill a ſow, we vſe to clay-pole with her, we ſcratch and tickle her ſides and throat, and this cauſeth her to lie downe,<note place="margin">Senec. de Doct. prine.</note> ſo that we thereby doe with her what we liſt; ſuch mens throats doth Gods prophet liken vnto open ſepulcres, for that they are very glorious without, but very loathſome within,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13.</note> for many of theſe vnder the ſhew of a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt friend cloke the malice of a
<pb facs="tcp:3397:42"/>mortall foe, the typ of the ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue ſoundeth not alwayes the depth of the heart; It is better then, I thinke, to fall among a ſort of rauens, then amongſt flattering companions, in that the rauens neuer eate a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till hee be dead, but theſe Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, will not ſpare to deuour him, euen while he is aliue, well then, they may ſeeme gold, tho they be but Indian braſſe; and what thinkeſt thou,<note place="margin">Ariſt. de me morab.</note> my ſoule, they may proue, when as the depth of their hearts ſhall bee ſounded, though now they ſound more ſhril then the pureſt Latin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Tinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 32.</hi> On the ſame.</head>
               <p>THe Chamelion changeth the colour of his skinne into the colour of its obiect, and this is the cauſe why they are ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome caught, or yet eſpied, for run they on the graſſe they ſeem greene, run they on the lately plowed ground they appeare like a mole-hill, runne they on chalkie ground, they ſeeme white, nay runne they on what ground they will, they ſeeme that whereon they runne; then let flatterers be like Camelions, who are drunkards with the drunkard, ſwearers with the ſwearer, Atheiſts with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, Papiſts with the Papiſts, and yet good Chriſtian Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb facs="tcp:3397:43"/>with the truely religious Proteſtant; theſe baſe abiectes are apt for all obiects, capable of all colours, they cloke hate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the habit of holineſſe, craft puts on him the attire of policie, malice the ſhape of courage, raſhnes the title of valour, and ſuperſtition the zealous appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of religion, thus abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vices walke along the ſtreets masked in the habit of vertues, and faire complezions haue oftentimes filthie conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; alas poore tel-troth, alas poore trueth, how art thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet with ſecret enemies, none (ſome ſay) tels trueth, but either children or fooles, well then be thou a child in the kingdome of heauen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> be thou a foole in the wiſdome of this world; alas poore truth what will become of thee? thou art a vertue indeed,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:43"/>but yet not guarded with any one friend, nor regarded of any, for what alacke, ſaith my ſoule, that theſe hypocrites do in their hearts, whenas they ſeeme to loue her, and thus outwardly to feigne and flatter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Hate her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 33.</hi> On the ſame.</head>
               <p>THe world now is come to ſuch a paſſe, that euery me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicall fellow, that euery tradſ-man hath his wordes of Arte, his fine painted ſpeeches, gards of eloquence, braue illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and a thouſand more lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trickes only to nyme, coſen, and deceiue; his words ſhall bee ſmooth yet not plaine, to draw on their falſe purpoſes, therfore ſeeing that their ſpeeches are
<pb facs="tcp:3397:44"/>onely feined words of Arte, we wil exclude them out of the true predicament of ſubſtance; what ſhould a man ſay to ſuch diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers, ſuch catiffe counterfeits, whenas they ſhal vſe the words of a good Chriſtian, by anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in trueth, yes verely, in very deed it coſt me ſo much; or it is ſo, when as if the trueth were knowen, a lye were manifeſt; helpe me then good Eccho, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond me O my ſoule, and tel me how thou wouldeſt anſwer ſuch a one, whenas hee ſhould moſt falſely, and moſt ſhamefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and ſay moſt impudently, it coſt mee ſo much, or it is ſo in very deede its ſo truely,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> You lie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 34.</hi> The reward of a lyar with a ſound terrour for the hypocrite.</head>
               <p>INdeed as I remember, one Philoſopher ſaith, that a man cannot better reward a lyar then in not beleeuing what hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, yet <hi>De virtute loqui mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt, virtutibus vti, hic labor hoc opus eſt,</hi> It is a very eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſpeake well, but a very difficult thing to doe well; thriſe happie then are they, (let the world eſteeme them as it liſt) whoſe liues are coreſpondent to their lines, and whoſe workes anſwere their words, but theſe halfe-faced Chriſtians, theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Neuters, are moſt loathſome and abhominable in the Church of God, <hi>Paul</hi> tels
<pb facs="tcp:3397:45"/>vs, that God is not mocked, let them take heed then, for ſurely if they make a ieſt and laughing ſtocke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.4.</note> of his ſeruice, the Lord will pay them home, the Lord will laugh them alſo to skorne and haue them in euerlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion; hee will recompence all their deeds, and with what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they meat vnto him, euen with the ſame will he meat vnto them againe, yea it ſhalbe preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe and runne ouer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 35.</hi> Mans neglect in Gods ſeruice is ſeuerely puniſhed.</head>
               <p>IF God would not haue man to haue ſerued him in true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, he would not haue made him in his owne image, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſhape and forme of a
<pb facs="tcp:3397:45"/>toad, of a ſnake, or of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther monſtrous creature; and ſurely he is not ſerued of vs as he requireth, he would haue our luſty daies, to be vſed to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but we put ouer our old and withered age to adore and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie him; when me thinkes our youthfull daies are fitteſt, and our old yeeres moſt vnapt; the wine that is firſt drawen out of the hogſhead we ſee is pure and freſh, but at length nothing els comes forth but grouns &amp; dregs,<note place="margin">Senec. Epi. <hi>109.</hi>
                  </note> thus the world drawes out the beſt of our dayes and we reſerue the ſcurffe and garbage for the Lord; and why are our youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dayes beſt? for that it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine whither wee ſhall liue to be old or no; and for that then our mindes are moſt tractable vnto goodnes; againe if it ſeeme hard vnto vs in our youthfull
<pb facs="tcp:3397:46"/>dayes, to betake our ſelues vnto Gods ſeruice, then to faſt and pray, then to curbe in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious appetites, how ſhall wee doe it in our olde doting yeeres, when as our bodies ſhall haue more need of cheriſhing then of chaſtening, more neede of feaſts then of faſts; if we find it vnpleaſant now to grub vp the root of ſinne after two or three yeeres groth, how more hard and vnpleaſant will it bee for vs, when twentie yeers more ſhall be adioyned vnto them: I it not a part of folly in that man who ſhall lead a ſcore of luſti horſes in his hand, and ride him ſelfe on ſome poore, thinne, and carinous iade, ſcarce able to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her ſelfe, and yet ſuffer all thoſe ſtrong ones to go emptie, and ſurely no leſſe fooliſh and vnreaſonable is hee who paſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:3397:46"/>ouer idly the luſtie time of his life, and reſerueth all the labour for feeble old age; yet this is the courſe and cuſtome almoſt of all ſorts of people, to deſire com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, for to paſſe the time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, when as there is nothing ſo ſure as this, that is, how that wee muſt all anſwere for euerie moment of time which is vainly paſt, &amp; what (ſaith Gods book) my ſoule is reſerued for him, who ſpends his daies idlely, and doth not paſſe his time well?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 36.</hi> A meditation on Chriſts miracle, which he wrought in Cana of Galiley.</head>
               <p>O Mercifull Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, vphold me that I fall not, whoſe legges are as pillars
<pb facs="tcp:3397:47"/>of marble ſet vpon ſockets of fine gold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.</note> whoſe countenance is as Lebanon, excellent as the Cedars, the firſt miracle which thou wroughteſt was at a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in Cana of Galile,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.</note> when thou there diddeſt turne ſixe ſtone pots filled vp to the brim with vvater into vvine, when the wine failed; ſo vvotke in my heart, O Lord, that all my vveak and vvateriſh prayers, vvherein is no ſtrength or force, may by thy holy ſpirit be tourned into ſuch as may pearſe the cloudes, and that the ſtrong ſauour ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may aſcend vp into thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, and be a ſvveete ſmelling ſacrifice vnto thee, O thou may ſtrength and my redeemer. And as Lord thou diddeſt keepe the beſt vvine vntill the laſt, ſo grant that vve likevviſe vvaxe better and better. O that vve grovv vp
<pb facs="tcp:3397:47"/>from grace to grace, and not wax worſe and worſe, that wee liue not more ciuill and ſober in our tender yeares then in our old age: that wee keepe not the worſt of our ſeruice vntill the laſt, but ſtill couet to pleaſe thee euerie day better and better, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the day of our Birth, vnto the houre of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 37.</hi> To be content.</head>
               <p>I See that the Diuell doth ſtill follow his old trade of iugg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, he hath caſt a glozing fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure to dazel our eyes, and with hay pas and repas he hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs all, for hee is not a ſtout and valiant man who ſtriketh firſt, but rather he who when he is ſtrooke, ſtriketh not againe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3397:48"/>takes all blowes patiently, vntill iuſt occaſion of reuenge ſhall be offered him: Hee is not a wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe mouth is filled with prittle prattele, who rowles out reproachfull quips and ieſts, but rather hee who loueth ſilence, that pythy-pythigoricall and excellent inſtitution, and hee is not a rich and wealthie man, whoſe trunkes are filled with golde, whoſe grounds are ſtuft vp with cattell, whoſe lands are laden with corne (except he bee therewith content) but rather he who liues all the weeke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly (through meare pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) with a meſſe of water-gruel: a dinner of greene hearbs ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> with content,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.17.</note> is better then a ſtalled Oxe, what ſhall riches profit a man?<note place="margin">Auguſt. in <hi>3.</hi> lib. de lib. Arbit.</note> nothing, for therein hangs couetouſneſſe, which is <hi>Inſatiabilis cupido,</hi> an
<pb facs="tcp:3397:48"/>vnſatiable luſting or an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable thirſting afterriches. If this be ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt al other men, I ſolie wonder at the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous: yet not becauſe they bee couetus, not becauſe they me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be but becauſe they be monſters and why monſters? for that they haue more then euer nature gaue them. I ſee then that the Diuell will helpe nature at a pinch, yea, and pinch nature at a helpe too, if at one time hee ſtrokes thin head, beſure at ſome other time hee will ſtrike thy backe; what though hee ſeemes to play with thee now, be bolde hee will pay thee home anon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 38.</hi> The couetouſneſſe of this age.</head>
               <p>VVEE all play the Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticians, wee vſe to ſet down the figure of one with three naughts and that ſay wee ſtands for a thouſand: if we doe one good deede with three bad nay with an hundred bad, wee thinke we haue done a thouſand good deeds, and that wee haue deſerued heauen with our good workes. The couetous mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſuch,<note place="margin">Seneca E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>73.</hi>
                  </note> that when as God doth caſt them downe a bleſſing from heauen, they ſwallow it downe with open chaps, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking any delight or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at all therewith: and are as ready like greedie dogges to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a ſecond morſell, as if they had left the former: Let me then
<pb facs="tcp:3397:49"/>giue them a little councell by the way, that is to tell them this, that he that eateth and drinketh too much, and therewith ſurfeits ſends to the Phyſitions with all ſpeed, asking them what diſeaſe it is, what griefe it is, and howe the paine may be mittigated, the Phiſition preſently returneth backward, and bids them vomit, telling him that hee ſhall finde that to be the beſt, and withall a verie preſent remedy: and what would not the Phyſitian of the ſoule thinke yee, in like manner giue the ſame Councell, vnto that man who is ſicke with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, by bidding him caſt vp,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 11.1.</note> &amp; caſt vpon the waters that money wherewith he did ſurfeit and take his ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Yes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 39.</hi> The reward of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous.</head>
               <p>SVch men little regard to ſhorten their liues, ſo that they may augment their riches, but me thinks goods purchaſed with an euill name are great loſſe, truely they are the bait of fin, and the ſnare of the ſoule: vnder theſe golden pilles is hid moſte deadlye poyſon, though they perceiue it not. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſuch men as theſe are good for no man, and worſe friends to themſelues; and why? for that in ſtealing from others, they robb themſelues, nay their owne ſoules of eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 40.</hi> The miſerable estate of miſers.</head>
               <p>OFtentimes haue I ſeene a man wanting money, yet neuer ſaw I money deſtitute of a maſter, ſurely wee may not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with the will of GOD, for golde ſerueth ſometimes to raiſe a man vp to honour, and again ſometimes to ſinke down his ſoule in the bottomleſſe pit of hell; for if it may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, a little while to ſet Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree aſide, then according vnto mans reaſon riches are ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon a couetous minded man; let him be a cold he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the warmer cloathed, if he be hungrie he is neither the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fed, if he be harbourleſſe he is neyther the better lodged, nor
<pb facs="tcp:3397:51"/>yet in any ſhew the more weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyer for them; what then though thou haſt much land and many Lordſhips, yet we cannot ſay that thou haſt riches, no more then wee can ſay this man hath an ague, for truely as the feuer is ſaid to hold and rule that man, who is therewith ſicke, ſo are riches ſaide to gouerne that man that poſſeſſeth them, riches hath him, he hath not them: he is ſtill a Subiect ſlaue to their becke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 41</hi> The little reſpect that worldly gluttons haue to learning in theſe daies.</head>
               <p>THus I ſee againe, that wee are al of vs welwillers to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetike, in that we all deſire
<pb facs="tcp:3397:51"/>to learne the golden number, or rather I thinke to number gold, but I tell you, that before wee come to heare this rule perfect we muſt firſt learne Subſtraction and Diuiſion as wel as Addition and Multiplication, for without them we cannot wel handle any queſtion, and eſpecially this one which our Maiſter Chriſt Ieſus ſhall propound vnto vs ſaying, <hi>Oughteſt not thou alſo to haue had pittie on thy fellowe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.33</note> 
                  <hi>euen as I had pittie on thee?</hi> But alas thogh wee bee expert and excellent in the latter two rules, yet in the former we are very dunces, for ſay now a poore man neuer ſo well beautified vvith good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and learning, commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a gluttonous Diues gate, hee ſhall finde it ſhut,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16.</note> hee may knocke often though no man anſwere, yet perhaps the dogs
<pb facs="tcp:3397:52"/>may faine vpon him and licke his ſores, &amp; bewaile his ſorrows when as if <hi>Diues</hi> himſelfe vvere there, he would churliſhly aske what art? vvhat wouldeſt thou haue? and if then this poore man ſhould anſwere crums, and that he is a poor Philoſopher, a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willer to learning, then would hee deride and laugh him to ſcorne and crie <hi>Ipſe licet venias muſis comitatus Homere, cum ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil attuleris ibis &amp;c.</hi> A lacke poore Homer, alacke poore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ſoule, moſt inhuman and vnnatural are men in theſe daies when as they are ſeruants, nay, bondſlaues vnto filthie durt and dung,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</note> for ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> thinkes, and they are vnſauerie and moſt loathſom dunghils, as I thinke, whereupon the earths garbage is caſt. Tell mee then plainely O my ſoule what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:3397:52"/>or dignitie, what loue amitie can hee finde there; or what is it elſe tell me in one word, that he doth purchaſe at each curmuggins gate?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Hate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 42.</hi> A comfort learning in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.</head>
               <p>THerefore ſeeing that enuy alway aſſociates vertue, enuied ſhall bee the hauen, wherein wee will ariue at eaſe and land at pleaſure al their ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous mockes and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, reproaches and mockes in this kinde are not ſo much as ſparkels to the one, but coales to the other, for though they doe ill in mocking vs, we may doe well in laughing
<pb facs="tcp:3397:53"/>them to ſcorne, and though they onely thinke Schollers to be but fooles, Schollers yet know them to be but aſſes, their daies, nay, their yeares haue beene long in this land, ſo that now they wink and kicke againſt their keepers, againſt their Paſtors and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,<note place="margin">Act. 9.5.</note> although it bee hard for them to kicke againſt the pricks: what haue I ſpoke truth my ſoule? yet me thinkes that they ſhould not for ſhame deſpiſe an Artiſt or a Scholler, ſurely they will bid ſuch a one welcome, what will they not? tell mee then what they will ſay to one that is skilfull in each Art and Science.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho. Hence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 43.</hi> Worth is reſpected before worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe now adaies.</head>
               <p>INdeed for Schollers to ſpeak learnedly vnto ſuch as are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and illiterate,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>and</hi> 3.18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6.</note> though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſomuch worldly wiſe, is to caſt pearles amongſt ſwine, and for Preachers to inſtruct thoſe who regard it not, is to giue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things vnto dogs. What hence with learning, what hence with liberall Arts and Sciences, why then belike they reſpect naught but money: I hope, my ſoule, they will doe ſomewhat vpon fauour, more then for lucre, tell me, for ſuppoſe a friend of myne do want a liuing (what ſaith my ſoule vnto him) ſhall not hee by fauour or friendſhip come by it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Buy it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 44.</hi> What the couetous moſt of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</head>
               <p>ALas poore Philoſopher, vvhat cannot thy pouertie moue them to pittie thee? no; nor yet thy complaints; no, me thinkes then, that thy learning ſhould much moue them: no, no; muſt the ſcholler buy his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing? alas, haue they no reſpect of him, if hee be poore and in miſerie, tell the world then, O my ſoule, what theſe greedie men of the world moſt deſire, for what they holde vp their hand, and ſtill cry moſt vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, come, come againe, come againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Gaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 45.</hi> God rewards the liberall giuer to the poore.</head>
               <p>HE then who intends to giue, muſt not be diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the loſſe of one benefit, but rather let him be like the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, who when he hath loſt one arrow, ſendeth forth another to finde the former, but if this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond will not preuaile, he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth foorth a third, &amp; ſtill ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on, vntill at length finding what hee ſought, retourneth home with ioy; One good turne will not returne ſo ſoone into our boſome as we expect; One good turne, one benefite muſt bring in another, and therfore if wee caſt our bread vpon the waters with <hi>Solomon,</hi> wee ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:3397:55"/>find it at length caſt vp vpon the ſhore with him, where euery man ſhall haue his ſhare, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes in this life whether they be good or euill;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> if good he ſhall finde them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, his bread ſhall be ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len thrice as bigge, as it was when it was firſt caſt on, when a cup of cold water ſhall not looſe his reward, this then is the beſt vſurie of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 46.</hi> The prayſe of liberalitie.</head>
               <p>VErely I haue thought with my ſelfe oftentimes, that man hath beene far worſe then the bruit beaſt or ſenceleſſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, for the moone giueth that light vnto the world, which ſhe receiueth of the Sunne: yet men
<pb facs="tcp:3397:55"/>will not beſtowe part of thoſe bleſſings receiued of God, vnto the benefit of their poore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed brethren: But alas they conſider not, that the deeds of the liberall doe more profit the giuer then benefit the receiuer: he that receiueth, receiueth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a temporall benefit, when as he that giueth, receiueth for his gift an eternall bleſſing, to doe good vnto poore men is a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſacrifice, the firſt to God, the ſecond to the man impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and the laſt and greateſt vnto himſelfe, nay vnto his own ſoule, if done with a true &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection of the heart, and not meritoriouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:3397:56"/>
            <div n="47" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 47.</hi> On the ſame, with a meditation on the words of Chriſt where he ſaith, It is eaſier for a cable rope to goe, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>OVr Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, that it is eaſier for a cable rope to goe through the eye of a needle then for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: yet let no rich man diſpaire, for a cable may eaſily goe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the eye of a needle, but then thus it muſt be worked, this rope muſt bee vnplatted, vntwiſted and deuided, and thread muſt be drawen after thread, vntill at length the whole rope bee brought through, ſo likewiſe the rich man muſt diuide his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtance, and giue it to the
<pb facs="tcp:3397:56"/>poore, he muſt caſt here a penny and there a pennie, here a piece of bread, and there a piece of bread, here a loafe vpon this water and there a loaſe vpon that water; for ſurely there is no vertue better then liberalitie, vnto the ſetting forth of Gods glorie, and vnto the purchaſing of good will among all men; praiſe and renowne doe alwaies abide in the porch of a cheereful giuer: here the oppreſſed is comforted; here the ſicke is ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, here the wounded is ſalued, here the hungry is fed; nay, in general tell me my ſoule, how is hee here dealt withall, that is any way pained or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Eaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 48.</hi> We cannot ſerue God and riches.</head>
               <p>IF wee cannot ſerue two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſters, that are of a contrary na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and eſſence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.24.</note> then ſurely we cannot ſerue God &amp; Mammon, God and riches; and know we not that,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Omne graue tendit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orſùm,</hi> euery heauie bodie ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and bendeth downeward, downe ward I meane to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the earth? then ſurely if we intend to ariſe with Chriſt, and not bee hindred in our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring vpward, we muſt caſt off from our heares the loue of thoſe earthly bodies, thoſe lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh earthie things; and mortifie our members which are on the earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 3.4.5</note> which hold and keepe vs from the true and liuely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping
<pb facs="tcp:3397:57"/>of God. God in the beginning made vs ſound and free, putting nothing before our eyes, which might intice vs vnto couetouſneſſe, he put gold and ſiluer vnder our feet, becauſe we ſhould loath, kicke it and tread vpon it, he put Iron amongſt it, becauſe we ſhould know that it breeds diſcord, diſſention and diſcontent; who then would thinke that man ſhould find it out, that man ſhould find out his owne deſtruction, yea and goe ſo farre, and ſeeke narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it in the earth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſet his whole delight, when as he knowes not how ſoone he ſhall depart from it, or it bee tooke from him, and ſeeing that <hi>Os homini ſublime dedit &amp;c.</hi> he made mans face to looke vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen, and only to haue his eyes fixed on celeſtial things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 49.</hi> We muſt leaue all behind vs.</head>
               <p>ME thinks I ſee here an vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin or an hedgehog vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a crab tree, rowling his back full of crabs, and yet is not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with contented, but for coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe ſake taketh one in his mouth too: but now againe me thinkes, ſeeing him running into his hole, wipes them all off, and carrieth only one with him, and that is in his mouth, I meane, one poore and naked ſoule: Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne againe, what foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh aſſes then are they, that will gaule their ſoules with the cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of treaſures, when as in the end of their iourney, it ſhall bee
<pb facs="tcp:3397:58"/>taken from them, &amp; they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues turned off into that colde ſtable where is nothing els but gnaſhing of teeth, nothing ſhal be left behind with them there, but their gald backs, their woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſcience which their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie packes of gold and ſiluer haue made, many yeeres before, being carried about with them, without euer any vnloading of them, and reſting or refreſhing of their bruſed ſoules, and what my ſoule is not this a great part of follies and of fooliſh madnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Yes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 50.</hi> A meditation on Chriſts clenſing of the leper.</head>
               <p>O Pittifull Chriſt, O ſweet Sauiour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>cant.</hi> 5.</note> whoſe cheekes
<pb facs="tcp:3397:59"/>are as a bed of ſpices, &amp; as ſweet flowers, whoſe lips are like lillies dropping downe pure mirrhe, hee ſcorned not to take vpon him our infirmities and to beare our ſickneſſes, he gaue ſight to the blind,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.</note> limbs to the lame, and cleanneſſe to the leper, hee loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed not to put forth his hand, for to touch his leproſie, and to tell him, I will, be thou cleane: the Law, my Lord, forbids any one to touch the vncleane, why diddeſt thou then? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but thou waſt aboue the law, thou madeſt the Law, therefore it was in thine owne power to obey it, or not: he touched not the leper for that hee could not without touching make him cleane, but becauſe wee faithleſſe ſoules ſhould ſee, that he was not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Law: and that hee did not feare the contagion as
<pb facs="tcp:3397:59"/>mortall men doe, and that hee could not be ſtained there-with, who healed others, he touched the Leaper, that thereby hee might teach vs humilitie, and compaſſion not deſpiſe any, not to abhorre any, and not to hold any as contemptible for any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of their bodies: My ſweete Lord when the Leapers cryed if thou wilt thou canſt make mee cleane, how ready waſt thou to anſwere him, I will, bee thou cleane; he returned him an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, before he had halfe vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſorrowfull requeſt; thou canſt make me cleane, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him like an Eccho, bee thou cleane, I will be thou clean, thou beleeueſt wel, and therefore wel thou ſhalt be clenſed, thou put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt no doubt in thy beleefe; and I will make no delay to heale thee: thou ſayeſt vnto mee, if
<pb facs="tcp:3397:60"/>thou wilt, behold I wil, thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou canſt make me cleane, I ſay to thee bee thou cleane: Oh heauenly anſwere, an anſwere of admirable clemency, an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of wonderfull pittie, and no leſſe then of diuine vertue &amp; mercie; that hee that was pure, the fountaine of all pureneſſe, nay puritie it ſelfe, ſhould thus touch the vncleane, that hee which was omnipotent ſhould thus touch the weake and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 51.</hi> Another on the clenſing of the ten Leapers, and of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulneſſe.</head>
               <p>AGaine we may read in the Goſpel by ſaint Luke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk</hi> 17.17</note> how that he healed tenne other Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb facs="tcp:3397:60"/>whereof nine of them were as vnthankeful for their clenſing as wee poore leprous ſoules are for any benefit that wee receiue at his hands, which made our Sauiour Chriſt ſay thus, there are ten clenſed, but where are the nine? there are none found that returned to giue God praiſe, ſaue onely this ſtraunger,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 13.2.3.45.46.</note> giue mee leaue a little therfore to chide theſe nine for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulneſſe, that ſo chiding them, we our ſelues may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our owne ingratitude. O vnthankefull Leapers, I tell you that before you came to Chriſt, ye had a couering vppon your lips, but now it being put away, and hauing free libertie to ſpeak me thinkes you ſhould returne backe and glorifie the name of God; before you came to Chriſt you were ſeparated from the
<pb facs="tcp:3397:61"/>companie of all men, but now hauing authoritie to goe where you liſt, why do you not now go and fall downe at his feete, and giue him thankes with that one Samaritan: and before you came to Chriſt, you were openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed vncleane, you were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, but now being clenſed me thinkes you ſhould ſing holy holy, holy, with a pure, cleane, and ſanctified ſoule; O yee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull Leapers, had yee but mollified hearts to conceiue, how great your miſerie was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you came vnto him, how great his mercie was towards you, and now how great your ingratitude is towards him, in not giuing him thankes for his clenſing of your moſt vglie and filthie bodies, it would cauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fountains of teares to runne downe your cheekes, O yee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull
<pb facs="tcp:3397:61"/>Leapers, had ye loued God in the third degree as yee loued Sathan, then ſhould hee haue had three of your hearts, whereas he had but one, and had you loued God but as well as you loued Sathan, then ſhould he haue had fiue of your hearts, againe, had ye but gone to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſtakes betwixt God and the Diuell, hee ſhould haue had halfe of them, halfe of them muſt needes haue fallen to his ſhare; &amp; laſtly had you conſidered your dutie towards him, and had don equitie and iuſtice with him then ſhould he haue had all, all ten of them, but now it ſeemes to me, me thinke, ſo, that you make a ieſt of Gods word, as many of vs in theſe daies doe, and that becauſe in the law he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to haue the tenth of all fruits offered vnto him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:3397:62"/>belike you giue him now the tenth heart too; a tything heart, and keepe nine for your owne vſe, and for whome you liſt; thus my ſweet Lord we ſtill gibe at thee and thy word; I pray God then once more that we be not deceiued for I know that thou wilt not be mocked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 24.</hi> On the lawleſſe tongue.</head>
               <p>HEe that clippeth the coyne of his Prince maketh it lighter to be weighed, but neuer the worſe to be touched, and he that by ſlaunderous reproaches ſeemes to impaire the credit of his friend; may make him ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter among the common ſort; but nothing at all hurteth his good name with the wiſe, who
<pb facs="tcp:3397:62"/>trie al golde by the touch-ſtone: for though ſlanders may blemiſh truth for a time, yet be ſure that truth will diſcouer ſlaunders at length: and what is the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that effecteth this, but the tongue? and what if it be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of all vanitie and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, yet is it neuer puniſhed though it offend neuer ſo highly: and therfore ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the vngodly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.4.</note> with our tongues will wee preuaile, our tongues are our owne, and who is Lord ouer vs? O lawleſſe tongue, thou ſtill eſcapeſt when as the Innocent and harmeleſſe hands, the feet, eares and necke for thee and thine offences are puniſhed, tormented and tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 53.</hi> Enuie ſtriketh at others but woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe.</head>
               <p>MEthinkes I ſee an Archer in the world who hath a quiuer full of poyſoning ſhaftes, he ſhooteth at others, and woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth himſelfe, and this is hee who maketh himſelfe vicious with other mens vertue, he ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth with other mens plentie, for this is he,<note place="margin">Horat.</note> who <hi>Alterius rebus macreſcit opimis.</hi> The cuſtome of this age is eyther to enuy or to mocke, he that is wiſe, vertuous and godly is enuied, hee that is fooliſh, vndiſcreet and vicious, is laught at, but of theſe two it is better for thee, therefore chooſe rather to bee enuied for thy knowledge then to be laught at
<pb facs="tcp:3397:63"/>for thine ignorance, and if it bee ſo that thou art enuied, enuy not againe, leaſt that thou enuying him and he enuying thee, God is angry with you both; and if thou art likewiſe curſed curſe not againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. 16. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 27.</note> leaſt that thou cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him and hee curſing thee, God curſe both and bleſſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 54.</hi> The malitious ſcoffings of theſe times.</head>
               <p>SVch is the ſcoffing malice of theſe daies, that when men execute their office throgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; why then forſooth they bee verie officious, if they be zelous &amp; deuout, they are thought pure and preciſe, if liberall and doe good deeds, then be they popiſh,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:64"/>ſo that the vertuouſly minded man hath naught elſe giuen him heere among vs, but ſome ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous nickname, and ſurely it was euen ſo in our Sauiours time, for <hi>Iohn</hi> came neither ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nor drinking and they the vulgar ſort ſaid that he had a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.15</note> and the ſonne of man came eating and drinking both,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.18 19.</note> and they ſaid behold a glutton and a wine-bibber, a friend vnto pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and ſinners. Many there are that delight in this deriding and laughing at their neighbors: indeed to play the ſcoffing foole well, is a ſigne of ſome witte, but ſmall wiſdome, though ſome bee of opinion, that hee which plaies the fooles part, is the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of all the company; yet my minde is not ſo: for I know this that whoſoeuer is maintained by one man to diſgrace another,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:64"/>is a ſeruill foole, he is a foole and a ſlaue too, but where dwel theſe carping wormes, one can hardly finde them, tell mee thou my ſoule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Io.</hi> 3.19.20</note> what places they inhabite moſt, that are ſuch reproachfull ſcorners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Corners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 55</hi> How the malitious Papiſts inuent miſchiefe and practiſe it.</head>
               <p>INdeed he that doth euil, hateth the light, leaſt that his deedes ſhould be reprooued, and a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of this hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malice haue I eſpyed in thoſe butcherlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebels, who thought with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and the diuell, not onely to take vp with their baſe and vulgar pawnes, our Knights, our Biſhops, and our moſt gratious
<pb facs="tcp:3397:65"/>Queene, but alſo to giue our great, our wiſe and moſte religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous king, an ineuitable checke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, but God that <hi>Ens entium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. in meta. Pſal.</note> to our great comforts, hath took downe their edge, the ſnare is broken, and wee are deliuered. But alas my ſoule, what woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue cried ſtil vnto Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, if they had obteined their diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh plot at the houſe of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Lament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 56.</hi> All treaſon in time will be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</head>
               <p>VVHatſoeuer villany the heart doeth thinke, in proceſſe of time, the worm of conſcience will bewray, wee ſee that ſparkles raked vp in cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:65"/>will at laſt begin to glow and manifeſt flame; and treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hid in ſilence, and obſcured for a time, will at length breath forth, and cry for reuenge, then if the bead of my bow be placed aright, I wil a little leuel at thoſe who dwell in Pater noſter row; Firſt, me thinks that their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is moſt impure, and this may ſeeme at the firſt glance to bee the reaſon thereof; for that they liue neerer the Aequinoctiall line then the North pole; they haue more heat then cold, and this cauſeth their rebellion to be flie-blowne, by Belzebub the prince of flyes, for tell me what theſe rebellious ſoules doe, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery word for the moſt part that they doe vtter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Erre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 57.</hi> Error, what it is.</head>
               <p>TO wander from the trueth doth betoken ignorance, and to deſpiſe the trueth, doth ſhew an obſtinate hart, and what doth my ſoule account mans greateſt ſhame, and his ſoules ſharpeſt terrour?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Errour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 58.</hi> Wee neede not the Popes Buls.</head>
               <p>I Like not well their diriges, their bulles and pardons: if Chriſt Ieſus be ſufficient inough to pardon our ſinnes, let them then driue backe againe their Buls to Rome, for our contrey,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:66"/>the Lord be praiſed, will not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford graſing for ſuch cattell, our paſture is not for them: we need not the hornes, nor yet the hide, wee need not the hornes for to make vs a lanterne to light vs to heauen, for he is the true light that lighteneth euery one, which commeth into the world, and his word is a lanterne vnto our feet and a light vnto our paths, and we need not the hide for to make vs ſhoes, for God wil giue his Angels charge ouer all true beleeuers to keepe them in all their waies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105.</note> that they daſh not their feet againſt a ſtone: he wil keepe all the faithfull in their heauenly iourney,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.11 12.</note> that they gaul not the ſoles of their ſoules with the grauell of the world, and what now thinketh my ſoule, concerning their prayers for the dead, or what, to be ſhort, doe
<pb facs="tcp:3397:67"/>they ſhew themſelues by their mumming Maſſes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Aſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 59.</hi> Superſtitions alwaies inuented by the Popes for lucre ſake.</head>
               <p>BVt tell me what the reaſon is, that they giue pardons for an hundred yeere, for two, or for moe: nay in generall, what is the fruit and iſſue of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery popiſh ceremonie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 60.</hi> What they worſhip and adore.</head>
               <p>ANd finally, what doe theſe blinde leaders of the blind, what doe theſe blind buſtards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore
<pb facs="tcp:3397:67"/>and worſhip in their maſſes and creeping pilgrimages?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Images.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 61.</hi> A meditation on Chriſts hiring labourers in his vineyard, and agreeing with them for a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie a day.</head>
               <p>O Sweete Ieſus, thou haſt taught vs in thy Goſpell that the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is like vnto a certaine houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, which went out at the dawning of the day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.1.2.</note> to hire la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into his vineyard, and when euen was come, hee gaue euery man a pennie; this day ſurely is the whole time of our life, and when wee waxe old, it begins then to waxe night, for then the day with vs is euen at
<pb facs="tcp:3397:68"/>an end; and therefore Chriſt himſelfe when hee liued bodily here on the earth ſaid, I muſt worke the works of him that ſent me while it is day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.4.</note> for the night commeth when no man can worke; When our eyes are ſhut how can we then ſee to do good? when our tongues cleaue to the roofe of our mouths, how then can we cry Hoſanna? when our hands are dried vp, how can we then ſtretch them foorth to giue? while we haue time ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs doe good;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.</note> Let vs work, let vs labour in the Lords vineyard, that euery one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a pennie. For ſurely by this word, a pennie, is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the reward of eternal life; for as a pennie is of a circular or round figure, whoſe circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence hath no end, ſo ſhall the reward of Gods labourers bee
<pb facs="tcp:3397:68"/>without end, with out any limit, or terme of yeeres; God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is this reward, according vnto that which he ſpoke vnto <hi>Abraham;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44</note> Feare not <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> for I am thy buckler and thine exceeding great reward, thou O Lord art all goodneſſe, all richneſſe, thou art that pearle of great price, which when a man hath found for ioy telleth no man, but departeth and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all that he hath, ſo that hee may buy the field wherein it is; further he which hath this pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie after a certaine ſort, hath all things. For as we ſee here in this world, that whatſoeuer a man will haue, hee muſt buy, and ſo come by it, by the pennie, and for it he may haue what he will, and in like manner that reward that pennie hath in it all things that may be deſired: that which
<pb facs="tcp:3397:69"/>neither the eye hath ſeene at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time, nor the eare heard, nor yet the heart of man euer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; And that a pennie hath the kings picture ingrauen vpon it, what doth it ſignifie els, but the perfect and pure Image of God in the elect, when wee all behold, as in a mirrour, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord with open face, and are changed into the ſame image, from glorie to glorie, as by the ſpirit of the Lord.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.</note> And again it is ſaid, that thoſe which he knew before, he did alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate, to be made like to the image of his ſonne. Graunt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O ſweet Sauiour, O ſweete Lord, that wee may faithfully worke in thy vineyard, and neuer be wearie of well doing, ſo that when euen ſhall come when we ſhall depart this life, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue euery one of vs a pennie,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:69"/>euerlaſting life and eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, and ſo euer be refreſhed with thy glorious image, with the bright beams of thine euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhining countenance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 62.</hi> The wicked and their reward.</head>
               <p>I Marueile, my ſoule, into what monſter the world is turned, ſinne and villany did neuer skul ſo much together as now it doth; for the cuſtome of this age is, to paine and pine the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for to paint the backe: all ſeeke honour &amp; renowne with a iuſtling vaine glorie and aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring impudencie, ſome vſe to paint white their faces, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour black their ſoules, of white lead is the complexion made, which coueteth the center, for
<pb facs="tcp:3397:70"/>that it is ponderous and heauie, I meane, not euery heauie and penitent ſoule, but euery lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh piece of lead, aſſayes down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the pit of hel the centre of all thoſe that are worldlings that are of the world: a pit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bottome, a fier without light,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt. Mat.</hi> 24.30 <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.43.</note> and an heat without heat, for there ſhal be cold, cold, and gnaſhing of teeth: yet there ſhal thoſe wretches burne in fier co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, they ſhall feele all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoeuer, ſo that they ſhal haue a death without death, and an end without an end, and why? for that with blacke vgly ſinne, they colour their ſoules, ſinne is the colour, the diuel the painter, and cuſtome (which is as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>altera na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura,</hi> a ſecond nature) is the oyle which keepes that doolefull co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour on ſtill, ſo that no ſtormes
<pb facs="tcp:3397:70"/>of the Lords wrath, no thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps againſt diſobedience can beat it off, ne yet can any ſmiles of his mercie once ſoken or looſe it, nor yet can any ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine daies of ioy promiſed melt it away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 63.</hi> Not to be loftie but lowly.</head>
               <p>PErhappes thou paſſing by ſome one of thine inferiors, who regard not thy deſerts, nor yet reſpect thy worthines, thou art therefore mal-content for a long time afterwards, thinking with thy ſelfe that ſome dutie or reuerence might haue beene ſhewen thee; if then thou wilt pacifie theſe inward broyles, as he reſpects thee not, ſo neither doe thou thy ſelfe reſpect thy
<pb facs="tcp:3397:71"/>ſelfe, if he cannot caſt his eye vp, ſo high as vnto the flag of thine honour, do thou therefore pluck it downe, and humble thy ſelfe, that all may behold it, fret not thy ſelfe at his vnmannerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, but rather ſmile therat, ſmile at his groſſe, and vnſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carriage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 64.</hi> The downefall of pride and the praiſe of humilitie.</head>
               <p>SAthan doth with the vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious, who lift themſelues aboue other men, as the crowe doth hauing an hard nut in her bill, the which ſhe cannot eaſily crack, ſhe beareth vp on high in the ayre, and from thence let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it fall down alow on a ſtone where it breaketh into many
<pb facs="tcp:3397:71"/>peeces, ſo that at length ſhe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth and cateth it vp: And the diuel rayſeth the proud man to honour, that thereby hee may bring him low, letting him fall down on the hard paines of hell, and ſo deuoure him: pride and fier are werie like, for often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times haue I ſeene a ſeething pot running ouer into the fier, laying the heate thereof, and ſo conſequentlie become cold, the pot is cold, the fier is out, and is not the fier cauſe of its owne death,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> &amp; the pot the cauſe of its owne coldneſſe? ſurely yes, and hee likewiſe that ſpraineth his arme by reaching vp on high, is the ſole cauſe of his owne griefe. I ſee that high hopes haue oftentimes hard euents, high reaching armes are beared vp in ſcarfes, and ſuch as doe ſnatch at the bough doe moſte
<pb facs="tcp:3397:72"/>commonly ſtumble at the root; tel me then my ſoule how a man ought to behaue himſelfe, or what hee muſt be, whereby hee may ſeldome fall downe on the ground,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.14</note> or yet thereon once ſo much as ſtumble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Humble.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 65.</hi> On the ſame.</head>
               <p>AT the winnowing of corne the chaffe being lighteſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.4.</note> mounteth aloft, the winde car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth it abroad where it liſt, and where it is loſt, but the Corne which is heauieſt, abideth a low on the ground, and is gathered vp and put into the Garners of the farmer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.30</note> &amp; kept for the profit of the common-weale, when as in the meane time the chaffe is burnt, loſt, and deuoured by
<pb facs="tcp:3397:72"/>beaſts: ſo pride a vapour that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth high preſently vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away into ſmoak, ye, euen into nothing: when then is the beſt time to be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble? in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no, for that is ſcarſe praiſe-worthy: then a man of neceſſitie muſt be humble, leaſt that hee makes a great fier in a little cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: the beſt time to be humble is in the middeſt of proſperitie, and this is praiſe-worthy, it is worthy of mans commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, commendable before men here on earth, and commaunded by God aboue in heauen: yet oftentimes the greater the brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the bigger his lookes, the ſmaller roſt, the greater boaſt, and what ſaith my ſoule, are they commonly cloathed with moſt, that vſe theſe high-vaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting brags?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Ragges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 66.</hi> There is no reaſon why men ſhould be proud.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J</hi> Would then that ſuch men would once againe ſtand on tipto on the mount of meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I would they would conſider with indifferent eyes what our bodies are in very deede, how beautifull ſoeuer they appeare to our outward ſight, tell me my ſoule what other thing is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of man, but only acorrupt and tainted veſſell, which inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſowreth and corrupteth whatſoeuer liquor is powred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it?<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> what other thing is a mans body, but onely a filthy dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, couered ouer with ſnow, which outwardlie appeareth white, and within is full of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:73"/>filth, and vncleaneſſe? what muckhill is ſo filthy? what ſink auoideth ſuch foule and filthie ſtuffe out of his channels, as a mans body dooth by ſeuerall meanes and waies? and why then O earth and aſhes ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou be proud? why ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou eſteeme thy ſelfe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much and be ſo vainely concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for tell me my ſoule, what mans body doth doe to any thing that ſhal ſtay in it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Staine it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 67.</hi> All things vaniſh ſaue a good name.</head>
               <p>ARt thou faire and welfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, praiſe not thy ſelfe, for the Lillie, though it be white yet it ſtinketh, art thou bigge, ſtrong, and of high ſtature, bee
<pb facs="tcp:3397:74"/>not vaine-glorious: for great &amp; mightie things are oftentimes comberſom: art thou vertuous, and yet praiſe not thy ſelfe, leaſt that thou become proud, and ſo vicious: art thou vertuous; now all men will ſpeake well of thee, it is onely vertue and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe that maketh foule things faire, and faire gratious: all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gifts of nature may ſoone be taken away, euen when one is aliue; the tall man many grow crooked, the faire face may bee ſhriuelled, the rich man may bee impoueriſheds, his ſilkes and veluets may be pluckt off from his back, his Iewels ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his eares, his rings from his fingers, when as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtus poſt funera vinit:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> vertue though it ſeemes to be dead, being obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red while hee liues, ſhall neuer dye, it ſhall liue after death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 68.</hi> One man thinketh that all is too much that another hath.</head>
               <p>FInally, I meruaile who can ſay and not counterfeit, I am contented with my eſtate, for I ſee that the ſhoomaker treads ſtately in the eyes of the Cobler, the Braſier gliſters before the face of the Tinker, and the Prieſt ſings ſweet in the eares of the Clark, would not a Pedler be a Mercer, and the Mercer a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, would not the Atturney be a Counceller, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellot a Iudge; thus many men climbe the high Cedars of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, but the boughes thereof being rotten they fall moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly vpon the ground: it is better then to gather grapes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly
<pb facs="tcp:3397:75"/>from that law, &amp; yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhrub, then to tryumph on the putrified armes of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Caedar;<note place="margin">Ouid de Triſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui iacet in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra non habet vnde cadat,</hi> when <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carus Icarcas nomme fecit aquas.</hi> Nay, what thinkeſt thou my ſoule, what will fortune (If I may ſo ſpeake) let any ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minde eſcape? for at whom doth ſhee aime with her dart ſo fatall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> At all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 69.</hi> A Meditation on Eliſha his put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Salt into a new cruſe &amp; by caſting it into the waters.</head>
               <p>WE reade that <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet by putting ſalt into a new cruiſe, and by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting it into the Springs of the waters, theſe waters that were
<pb facs="tcp:3397:75"/>naught and vnwholeſome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 16</note> were made good and delightful, what ſhall we conceiue heare by thoſe waters of Iericho, but the teadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous combats of a bad conſcience heare in this life, and what by this new cruiſe, but an heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by repentance?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6.</note> Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſalt doth ſignifie the power of the word of God: for as by the ſprinkling of ſalt on freſh meate it is kept from maggots, from Flie-blotes, and from all corruption whatſoeuer, and hee whoſe ſoule is ſeaſoned with the word of God, is preſerued from all the corruption of ſinne, and from that worme which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually knaweth the conſcience, and neuer dyeth: O my ſweete Lord, grant then that wee may bee true veſſels, filled with this myſticall ſalt, that we may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the teadiouſneſſe of this
<pb facs="tcp:3397:76"/>life.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5</note> Thou haſt promiſed that although wee weepe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the world reioyce, &amp; although we ſorrow now, yet our ſorrow ſhall be turned into ioy: Indeede it is thy word O Lord, whereby wee haue reſt in our labours, whereby wee haue mirth in our mourning &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are rich in pouertie, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are exalted through hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and through contempt wee are made glorious; this is that meale of the prophet which made ſweet the bitter pottage,<note place="margin">4. <hi>King.</hi> 4:</note> and when as they cried through the bitterneſſe of thoſe gourds, that were put therein, <hi>mors in ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, mors in olla,</hi> death is in the pot oh death is in the pot; and by that meale oh Lord thy word which is the breade of life, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we ſeeme to be dead, yet are we ſtill renued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 70.</hi> Old age not to be deſpiſed.</head>
               <p>IT is a thing moſt fooliſh in the ſight of good men, and an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence moſt heynous before God, to mocke olde men who are as wee ſhall bee, and who were as wee are now. Age, Time and death, theſe three a man may fore-thinke of, but neuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 71.</hi> Wiſdome and diſcretion goe not alway by yeares.</head>
               <p>YOuth neuer runneth wel ſay we, vnleſſe age holdeth the bridle, this ſeemes to be true &amp; it is ſo: but alas wiſdom conſiſts not onely in age as the vulgar
<pb facs="tcp:3397:77"/>ſort of people cenſure, for the young man beardleſſe may bee as wiſe as the gray head, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward grauitie argues wiſdome verie ſeldome, but wiſdome continually ſhewes grauitie, the young man fearing God is both graue and wiſe; and he that hath this feare before him, is the ſoules beſt councellour;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5</note> And this cannot a father bequeath vnto his Sonne; it goes not by birth, not by our firſt birth which is full of corruption, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we be regenerate and born a new, and then this latter birth extinguiſheth the flames of the former; Neither as I ſaid before doth diſcretion goe by yeares, for there are manye old fooles giuen vp wholy to ſenſualitie, which ſolely belongeth to the beaſt amongſt all creatures, and there are many young men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed
<pb facs="tcp:3397:77"/>to ciuilitie, and this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth vnto man, the image of God, euen the beſt of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; this is that vvhich ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men on the earth famous, in the earth glorious, and in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue the earth immortall, immortall both in ſoule and bodie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 72.</hi> The praiſe of loue and amitie.</head>
               <p>MEn in the beginning buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded townes for ſocietie and ſafetie, but now a man may finde more friendſhip in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe amongſt beares and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, then he can find in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey wherein he was borne; but ſurely I haue thought with my ſelfe, that if men liue neuer ſo richly and at variance, their liues
<pb facs="tcp:3397:78"/>are farre worſe then death, for it is a ſecond hell, as wee terme it; friendſhip is the chiefeſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament that graceth Chriſtians, whereby many mens hearts and wils are vnited in one: a boſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend, me thinkes, is a pretious iewell, fit to weare about ones necke, within whoſe boſome a man may vnload his ſorrowes, and vnfold his ſecrets, which he will either releiue with counſel, or els perſwade with reaſon, and if thou declare vnto him ioyfull newes he wil reioyce with thee, if dolefull and heauie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15</note> hee will mourn with thee, and in all thy affaires, thou ſhalt find him, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ipſe</hi> a ſecond ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 73.</hi> Men are ſoone mooued vnto wrath.</head>
               <p>BVt now alas, as the nature of the bruit beaſt is,<note place="margin">Plin. Senec. philoſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Ira cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> ſuch is the condition of man, trifles and vaine things doe moue vs vnto anger, a red cloth ſtirreth vp the bull, the venemous aſpe of Africk riſeth vp at a ſhadow, and a white cloth or table nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin mooueth vnto rage the bear and lyon; horſes, wolues, nay moſt things els, very fierce of nature, are troubled with the ſight of very ſmall and friuolous things, and in a manner with nothing, and euen ſo it fals out with peniſh &amp; froward people, that they are ſtroke with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conceit only and ſuſpition of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:79"/>a thing, ſo that now and then they are wrath, if a man wiſheth them neuer ſo well, or ſpeake them neuer ſo faire, euen at the putting forth of a queſtion, they are ſoone moued vnto rage: the vngodly,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> are fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euen from their mothers wombe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 74.</hi> The end of diſcord.</head>
               <p>IF a man will liue in reſt, it is better for him ſometimes to diſſemble a double wrong, then to reuenge a ſingle: let him ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee accounted a daſtardly coward, then a deſperate caitiffe; yet valour in rightfull cauſes is to be commended, and if done with diſcretion highly alſo to be regarded and rewarded,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5 26.</note> but othervviſe all miſchiefe, that
<pb facs="tcp:3397:79"/>may be, doth follovv the heeles of ſelfe-loue and diſcord, vvhat then my ſoule, had we beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace vvhile vve haue time and opportunitie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Vnitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 75.</hi> A meditation on the diſciples filling of twelue baskets full of the broken meate that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained.</head>
               <p>WHerefore grant, O my ſweet Lord, that wee laying aſide all maliciouſneſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</note> and all guile, and diſſimulation, and enuie, and all euill ſpeaking, we may as new borne babes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the ſincere milke of thy word, that we may grow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. Feed our ſoules, O Lord, with the bread of life, that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:3397:80"/>foode; and giue vs thine heauenly grace, that ſo we ſpill none thereof, but gather vp the broken meat that nothing bee loſt: O thou whoſe mouth is as ſweet things and art wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable, this thou commandedſt thy diſciples,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.</note> and they gathered and filled twelue baskets full with the fragments of the fiue loaues and two fiſhes, but why ſhould there remain iuſt twelue baskets full, and no more nor leſſe? ſurely becauſe there were twelue Apoſtles, which thoſe twelue baskets did prefigure, who were filled with the bread of life, &amp; did nouriſh the ſoules of the beleeuers into euerlaſting life. But firſt. O my ſweet Lord before thou gaueſt the people to eate, thou diddeſt comaund them to ſit dovvne, and there vvas much graſſe in that plece,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:80"/>and therefore we who deſire to be fed, with the ſpirituall food,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> to be refreſhed with the ſweete dainties of the grace of God, and to come &amp; taſte how good and gratious the Lord is, muſt cruſh downe, kicke and deſpiſe the luſts of the fleſh, which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout the whole Scriptures is likened vnto graſſe: all fleſh is graſſe, ſaith the Prophet, and the glorie thereof as the flower of graſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.</note> let vs ſit downe then vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ground, vpon this graſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col:</hi> 4.5.</note> let vs chaſten our bodies, tame our inordinate affections, and continually bridle our rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hed-ſtrong luſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 76.</hi> On the fiue barlie loaues and the two fiſhes.</head>
               <p>FVrthermore, it is ſaid, that Ieſus tooke fiue barly loaues and two fiſhes: ſurely by theſe fiue barly loaues, wee may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the fiue bookes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> which he laid wide open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpirituall eyed, dayly and hourely to refreſh their ſoules therewith, and they may well be likened vnto ſo many barly loaues, from the auſteere and ſharpe decrees of the Law, that was contained in them: yet at the laſt, like a good father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would not ſuffer his children to eat any longer drie bread, hee added two fiſhes, which were diuided among
<pb facs="tcp:3397:81"/>them, that is, the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whoſe nature is to make pleaſant and moyſten the harſh drith of the loaues; the lawe killeth and is giuen to the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</note> but mercie &amp; trueth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 77.</hi> On drunkenneſſe and the beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof.</head>
               <p>MAny men thinke, that all friendſhippe conſiſteth in quaffing and carouſing, but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that is but drunken good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip: very heathens can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs from it, by telling vs that euery man will vnload his ſecrets in the boſome of a good man, but no man will tell them to a drunken man, wherefore a drunken man is not a good
<pb facs="tcp:3397:82"/>man,<note place="margin">Senec. Epi. <hi>84.</hi>
                  </note> and who knowes not this, that the tongue of ſuch a one, is not in his owne power; wee ſee that when new wine is put into any veſſell, whatſoeuer lieth hid in the bottome worketh ſoone vp vnto the top, and hee whoſe braines are oppreſſed therwith, doth vtter at his mouth whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer lyeth ſecret in the bottome of his heart, he can by no means keepe cloſe his ſtomacke: the drunken man, ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> is apt and prone vnto all villanie, as vnto wrath, murders, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, whoring and the like, and let all the world know this my ſoule; for whoſe ſaieſt thou are theſe monſtrous miſdeeds?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> His deeds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 78.</hi> The drunkards reward.</head>
               <p>ANd again, to whom is woe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 23.29</note> ſaith the wiſeman, to whom is ſo row, to whom are wounds, to whom are the rednes of the eyes? euen vnto him that ſets his delight in drinking: and tell me alſo my ſweet Eccho, thy opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, what may be the cauſe of many red pimpled faces, and therin of thoſe vnſeemely ſpots?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Pots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 79.</hi> Gaming their whole delight.</head>
               <p>ANd is this all, my ſoule, that they delight in, make they not ſome thing els halfe of their Paradice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Dice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 80.</hi> Where they are chiefly entertained and ſoothed vp in them wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</head>
               <p>ANd what places, for the moſt part, will allow of theſe wicked meetings, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate ſuch abominable ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Innes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 81.</hi> The fruit of drunkenneſſe.</head>
               <p>SVrely, this notorious vice, hath deuoured more then the ſea hath deuoured,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21.</note> the ſea ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the bodie onely, but this both ſoule and bodie; it infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the liuer, rotteth the lungs, dulleth the memorie, and bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all diſeaſes whatſoeuer:
<pb facs="tcp:3397:83"/>had I a deadly enemie, &amp; would faine ouer-come him, truely I could not wiſh him more harme then that hee were a drunkard, I ſhould not neede to make any warre againſt him, for I ſhould ſoone perſwade my ſelfe, that he wold in ſhort ſpace deſtroy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; God made mans ſoule of a liuing ſubſtance, but his body fraile and mortall, and for the ſoule he hath appointed ſpiritual foode, for the body temporall and tranſitorie, the firſt of theſe ſhall indure for euer, the latter only for a certain limitted time, wherefore man muſt not deſire to liue, ſo that the may eate and drinke, but ſo drinke and eate that he may liue: but now me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes that theſe Epicures greatly deceiue themſelues, for they eate and drinke, that they may die, for as hunger dooth
<pb facs="tcp:3397:84"/>drie vp the marrow,<note place="margin">Eratoſt benes Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus. Poe</note> ſo doth too-much pampering of the fleſh, conſume and ouerthrow the ſpirits and vital parts, for, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inum igni aequale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vim habet,</hi> ſaith one, wine and fier are both of one, force, both inflaming, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 82</hi> On filthy luſt and how it is ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed and ſmothered vp in theſe daies.</head>
               <p>VNbridled luſt is alſo an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of drunkenneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 42. <hi>verſe</hi> 11.</note> the Prophet Hoſea in his iiii. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, linkes them both together, yet many of our Prophets for feare of incurring diſpleaſure, will of incurring diſpleaſure, will not once name or take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them, they touch them indeed a little, but how? verie
<pb facs="tcp:3397:84"/>coldly; they glance at them, but they wil be ſure not to hit them, it is a very rude ſpeech, wherein any finne is named in particular, they beat the buſh, though they ſee the bird, ſurely that Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian who mindeth to recouer his patient, ſearcheth the verie bottom of the wound; if GOD then ſaith thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adulterie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.14</note> and if hee meanes as he ſaith, tell then the world plainely (O my ſoule) what are they whome God abhorres?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho</hi> Whores.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 83.</hi> To beware of Strumpets.</head>
               <p>MAny are caught through this ſweet poyſon. <hi>Diana,</hi> liues cloſely in the woods, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3397:85"/>liues prinily in her col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 7.10 11.12. <hi>&amp;c</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Bellona</hi> in her tent; but <hi>Lais</hi> that braſen-face ſhineth at Corinth, euen on the top of the high towers, I wonder when <hi>Venus</hi> will haue finiſhed her courſe, ſhe hath dominered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer other planets, ſhe hath been in her Apogaee, and in her exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation this long time; yet deſire not thou the beautie of the ſtrange woman in thy heart, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let her take thee with thy eye-lids ſaith <hi>Salomon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.25 26</note> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the whoriſh woman a man is brought to a morſell of bread, and a woman will hunt for the pretious life. Who then ſaiſt thou my ſoule muſt beware of theſe inticing ſtrumpets, theſe whoriſh women?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho,</hi> Yee men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 84.</hi> The Praiſe of Chastitie.</head>
               <p>THere is neuer a nauie of men ſailing out into the world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.24</note> but hath askul of pleaſure atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill vpon the puppe; which ſoone will drowne the whole ſhippe, vnleſſe they call and cry vpon that skilful Mariner Chriſt Ieſus, whome both windes and Seas obey. And amongſt all the inticing pleaſures of ſharpe combats of a Chriſtian ſoule, none is more ſore then the wars of a chaſte minde, in that the fight is continuall and the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie rare, and if the walles of chaſtitie be once battered down there is naught left praiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy eyther in man or woman; for this is ſhee which is the
<pb facs="tcp:3397:86"/>zeale of grace, the ſtaffe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, the marke of the iuſt, and the onely comfort in death: when as in the meane ſpace, luſt is an enemy to the purſe, a foe to the perſon, a canker to the mind, corroſiue to the conſcience, a weakener of the wit, &amp; a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bane both vnto ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo that he ſhall finde pleaſure and delight the path-way vnto perdition, he ſhal finde a wound and diſhonour, and his reproach ſhall neuer be put away.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.33</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 85,</hi> Swearers and their fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</head>
               <p>THe Dogge bites the ſtone, whoſe will is to bite him that caſt it, the traytour in heart defaceth the picture of the king, when as he cannot come neare
<pb facs="tcp:3397:86"/>his perſon and the Swearer, the drunkards copeſmate too, by blaſphemous oathes, teares the name of God, who if hee could would raize his eſſence, but hee may not reach it, Of all ſinnes ſwearing hath the leaſt pleaſure in it, and is moſte vnprofitable and moſt heynous and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and againe, me thinkes, that amongſt all ſinners the Swearer is moſt fooliſh, who cannot bee contented to ſinne ſecretly, but muſt needes call both God and man to witneſſe his impietie, how then can hee thinke to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape ſuch a preſumptuous fault as this, when as hee runnes wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly into ſin? ſurely the Lord hath ſaid that hee wil not holde him guiltleſſe; if he beleeues that there is a God, hee muſt beleeue this to bee true, but if hee will ſweare by the name of God, and
<pb facs="tcp:3397:87"/>yet thinke (as many doe) that there is no God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1</note> and as <hi>Dauids</hi> foole affirmes in his heart, then truely this man of al men is moſt ridiculous, who will ſweare by that which hee ſuppoſeth not to be: this is the faſhion of all ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing Atheiſts, then tel the world, O my ſoule, what ſuch men as theſe, what ſuch blaſphemers vſe to doe, (when one ſhall but ſpeake vnto them kindely) at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie word that they ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Sweare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 86.</hi> What God is.</head>
               <p>IT is not for a Chriſtian to make a ieſt of ſwearing:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.5</note> if hee ſweare he muſt ſweare in truth, in iudgement, and in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:87"/>for otherwiſe though a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſwear often, yet by my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent he ſhould ſeldome bee beleeued. And a guiltie conſcience cleared by an oath, is like vnto foule hands ſcowred with ſope, through which although they be made cleane, yet they ſmell verie rancke thereof a long time afterward, and a periured ſoule though it be cleared and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, in the ſight of the world, by forſwearing, yet that ſame oath adioyned to the former fact, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies the ſoule the more, that falſe kiſſe betraies it inwardlie though it cannot be deciphered by a long ſpace outwardly; then in concluſion tell me, and tell all men (my ſoule) what God that great thundering Iehouah moſt deteſts, and moſt deteſtfully Loathes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Oathes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 87.</hi> A Meditation on the betraying of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>O Sweet Chriſt, O ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, how waſt thou tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, for theſe ſinnes of ours, and the like;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.</note> come then my friends, let vs weepe together &amp; mourne, let teares runne down our checkes, and among all our louers let there be none to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.14.15.</note> let our ſtreets lament, let no man feaſt, let all our gates be deſolate, let our Prieſts ſigh, let virgins be diſcomfited, and let vs all bee in heauineſſe: for we haue ſinned, our ſinnes are great, and for them is the ſonne of GOD crucified; <hi>Iudas</hi> ſolde him, kiſt him and betraid him, he ſold him for thirty pence. O thou naughty
<pb facs="tcp:3397:88"/>Traitor, at what price doſt thou ſet the Lord of all creatures, at thirty pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? what my Lord ſold for thirtie pence? O what a vile and ſlender price is this for a Lord of ſuch maieſtie, certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a very beaſt in the ſhambles is commonly ſold for more. And doſt thou oh Traitour ſell for ſo ſmal a price almighty God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee ſetteth not thee at ſo ſmall a price, for ſo much as hee buieth thee with his owne moſt pretious blood; Oh what a great price and eſtimation, was that of man, and how baſe an eſtimation and price was this of God; God was ſolde for thirty pence, and man was bought with the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt bloud of God himſelfe: And when this <hi>Iudas</hi> had betrayed him, and was deliuered into the hands of the Iewes, ſee how each one giueth him buffets and
<pb facs="tcp:3397:89"/>and ſtroakes;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29 <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.65 <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.22 23.</note> ſee how they ſpit vpon that diuine face with their diueliſh mouthes: ſee how they hoodwinke his eyes, and ſtrike him on the face, ſcoffing and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting at him, ſaying, Aread who hath ſmitten thee? O my ſoule, great were the mockes and tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts hee ſuffered for thee, how pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently did he beare the ſpitting of thoſe infernal mouthes, that had himſelfe not long before, with the ſpittle of his owne mouth, reſtored a blind man to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſight, how ſuffered he their whippings, whoſe ſeruants were wont in his name with mightie power to whip the very diuels, how was hee crowned with thornes that crowned his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs with euerlaſting Garlands, how was he ſmitten on the face with palmes of mens hands, that giueth the palme of victorie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:3397:89"/>ſuch as be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querors; how was he robbed of his erthly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which cloatheth his ſaints with garments of immortallitie; how was heproffered moſt bitter gaule, that giueth vs the bread of life; how was hee offered Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to drink, that giueth the cup of ſaluation.<note place="margin">Haec omnia ſunt cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani.</note> Conſider moreouer at what time the Sauiour of the world was nailed to the Croſſe: how both the heauens and the earth were troubled, the Starres were obſcured, the elements di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, how the earth quaked, how the light was darkened when the ſunne turned away his eyes, and would not ſuffer his beames to ſhine vppon the earth, leaſt happilie it might ſee ſuch a great crueltie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:90"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 88.</hi> Our ſinnes the cauſe of Chriſts death.</head>
               <p>IF thou be not mooued to take compaſſion on our ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, ſeeing him in this doleful caſe for thy ſake, if now when he ſheds drops of blood through out all his body, thou canſt not ſhed any teares from thine eyes, thinke verily with thy ſelfe that thou haſt a very hard and ſtonie heart, and if thou canſt not weep for loue towards him, yet at the leaſt weepe for the multitude of thy ſinnes, for ſo much as they were the verie cauſe of this his agonie and greefe. Now the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters doe not whip him, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe the Souldiers crowne him with thornes, that do cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:3397:90"/>bloud to guſh out of his body, but it is thy very ſinnes &amp; offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thoſe are the thornes that do prick him, they are the ſpeare that do thruſt him into the ſide, they are torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tors that do afflict him, they are the heauy burthen that doe cauſe him to ſweat this ſo ſtrange &amp; wonderfull a blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſweat. Oh my ſweet Sauiour and Redeemer, Oh thou lambe of God that takeſt away the ſins of the world, how dearely haſt thou bought my ſaluation?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 89.</hi> They that are in authoritie muſt ſhew good examples.</head>
               <p>GOuernours eyther ſpirituall or temporall, ſinne more grieuouſly by example then by act; their act deſtroieth but one,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:91"/>their example may deſtroy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and therfore ſurely the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter account they are to render and the more circumſpectly to behaue themſelues, leaſt that in their owne precepts, they bee found faultie: the greater power then that one man hath aboue others, muſt teach him to excell in vertue aboue them: for what doth it profit an Emperor to be Lord and king ouer many king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, if on the other part he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come bondſlaue to many vices, titles of honour bee nothing worth if the life of the party bee bad, ſurely true nobilitie conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in dignitie, linage, large poſſeſſions and the like, but in wiſdom knowledge and vertue: and this nobility bringeth a man to dignitie in the kingdome of heauen, and as for this life it is not the place as fooliſh men ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:91"/>that makes the perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, but it is the perſon that maketh the place alwaies hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 90.</hi> The praiſe of ſilence.</head>
               <p>OF all vertues the chiefeſt is ſilence, for by it thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the imperfections of others, and concealeſt thine owne; for commonly emptie veſſels make the lowdeſt ſound, and men of the weakeſt wit, and leaſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie are the greateſt bablers; the heart of the foole ſaith <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racke</hi> is in his mouth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 21.26</note> but the mouth of a wiſe man is in his heart; then thinke this with thy ſelfe, before thou makeſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy counſell, that it is great follie, to thinke to haue that
<pb facs="tcp:3397:92"/>kept ſecret, by telling it vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, when as thou canſt not keepe it ſecret thy ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 91.</hi> The charitable man.</head>
               <p>WHoſoeuer drinketh of the ſweete ſprings of charitie, is apt and readie to all good, hee laboureth and is not wearie, he is wearie &amp; feeleth it not, bee feeleth it, but grieueth not: the malitious mock him but he regards them not: he is cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but he bleſſeth and curſeth not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 92.</hi> Parents muſt inſtruct their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</head>
               <p>SVrely that childe is not bound in duetie to loue thoſe his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb facs="tcp:3397:92"/>of whome hee neuer learnt any vertuous inſtruction, it is not enough for a man to ſay I haue a ſonne, except the can ſay I haue a ſonne fearing God, and profitable for the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale, and a father that would haue ſuch a ſonne, muſt teach him as well by good examples as by Godly admonitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 93.</hi> Miracles are euerie day to be ſeen in the world.</head>
               <p>SOme men looke daily for miracles from heauen, yet they regard not theſe myracles that are dayly ſent, euerie new borne babe beareth a wonder, but who eſteemes it worthy of admiration, tenne hundred men ten hundred countenances, all
<pb facs="tcp:3397:93"/>rare, all varying &amp; all ſingular to ſhew the ſingular rareneſſe of Gods power, ten hundred tongs ten hundred voyces, ſome ſharp ſome flatt, ſome ſhrill, ſome hoarſe, none alike, ten hundred mindes, ſome good, ſome bad and each one diſagreeing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 94.</hi> God doth not defire the death of a ſinner.</head>
               <p>A Good muſition hauing any key or ſtring of his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of tune, doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately cut it off, and caſt it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but either by ſtraining it higher, or ſlacking it down low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by little and little cauſeth it to agree, and God deſireth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reforme the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by ſmall corrections, then
<pb facs="tcp:3397:93"/>ſeeke to caſt them away for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie treſpaſſe, hee lifteth them vp high by heaping his bleſſings vpon them, to ſee whether or no, theſe his mercies will bend them, but if this wil not ſerue, he vſeth then to ſlacke his loving kindneſſe, and to thruſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on them; to trie whether theſe his threates will breake them, ſo that it may bee he will make them agree and tunable with his will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 95.</hi> We beleeue not that God is angrie with our ſinnes.</head>
               <p>GOd oftentimes ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> hath bent his bowe, and made ready his arrowes, to ſhoot at the wicked and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinner, and yet doe they
<pb facs="tcp:3397:94"/>not thinke that hee is angrie with their ſinnes. And often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times againe with moſte fatall and deadly ſhot, hath he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the roaring gunnes of his wrath, and fluſt many times in the pan, ſtill putting the Lenitie of his mercie in the touch-hole, betweene the barrell and it, to trie whether wee would take the winges of repentance, and flie away; yet ſet wee ſtill chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp and pruning of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils like fooliſh birds, thinking nothing, not at all expecting death, or yet any danger to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, ſo that at length wee tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and totter headlong ouer the pearch, wheron we thought we ſat moſt ſecure. Surely men in theſe daies do preſumptuouſly depend vppon Gods patience: they thinke him to bee a God of waxe, whome they may meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphiſe
<pb facs="tcp:3397:94"/>and change into what ſhape they pleaſe, whom they may melt and turne into what faſhion they wil, but I feare that in this their tempring of him, he will ſo ſtick to the skirts of all preſumptuous offenders, that all the waters in the broad ſeas wil not be able to waſh all their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeering off, to waſh cleane and cleanſe their ſoules from that horrible ſinne of preſumption, God will not be mocked, <hi>Non eſt ludendum cùm ſanctis,</hi> It is ill ieſting with edge tooles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 96.</hi> We muſt humble our ſelues before God.</head>
               <p>GOD is loftie and God is lowly, he is pitifull, and he is terrible, he is great in compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and great alſo in confuſion, and in both without paſſion; if
<pb facs="tcp:3397:95"/>thou doeſt lift vp thy ſelfe vnto him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 16 4.</note> he flyeth from thee; but if thou humbleſt thy ſelfe and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt the ground with thy face, he ſoone lighteth vpon thy backe, God is a ſpirit, and like a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; which when thou ariſeſt vp vaniſheth away from thee; the onely way then to catch it is to fall downe vpon it, to fall downe vpon thy knees with the Publican and crie, Lord haue mercie vpon me a ſinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 97.</hi> We can ſee a moat in our brothers eye, but not the beame in our owne.</head>
               <p>IT is a ſtrange matter to ſeé, how euery man will gaze and wonder at a foole, yet no man will vouchſafe ſo much as to looke vpon his owne deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:95"/>me thinkes, moſt men haue the eyes of thoſe counterfeiting Lamiae,<note place="margin">Eraſ. Rothe.</note> they can ſee a farre off, yet not diſcerne hard by; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne then a foole, and ſee thy ſelfe, or ſee a foole, and wonder at thy ſelfe: moſt of the worlds wiſeſt men haue ſome babble, Satans Scepter, Vice the babble, Sinne the ſcepter, whereby the diuels kingdome is vpholden.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 98.</hi> Vaine glorie a meere vanitie.</head>
               <p>MAny men hunt after vaine glorie, they runne vp and downe to catch a feather; and pray what is it but a fether? euen as light as nothing, they dreame that they haue mountaines of gold; but when they awake out of their fleep of blind ignorance they ſhall finde iuſt nothing at all in their handes, and what is
<pb facs="tcp:3397:96"/>praiſe and renowne when they haue it, for which they gaped for ſo long, truely it is not worth three points, for that it is onely the breath of ſome fewe mens mouthes, the men may die, their mindes may alter vpon euery light occaſion, which now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him great, now little and now nothing at all; our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, was receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieruſalem with trimph of Hoſanna, crying, bleſſed is hee that commeth in the name of the Lord, Hoſanna in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.20</note> and caſting their apparell vpon him, and cutting downe branches and ſtrawing them in the way, but not long after this they cried as faſt, crucifie cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, crucifie him, crucifie him, let him be crucified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:96"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 99.</hi> We loue not to be told of our faults.</head>
               <p>THough it bee a fault gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally for all men to ſinne, yet very few can indure to heare their ſinnes repeated or reproued, but wee muſt heare what we would not, when as we doe what wee ſhould not, and what though the hearing therof bee vnpleaſant to thy ſoule, yet me thinkes the perſwaſions to amendment ſhould bee ſweet: mixe one with the other; and drowne the bitter and vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant taſte of reprehenſion, with a ſweete and delectable reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to lead a more godly and Chriſtianlike life, drowne it with a ſweet repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:97"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 100.</hi> Wee muſt haue patience in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the will of God.</head>
               <p>ANd ſurely patience in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the will of God muſt needes be very good and neceſſarie, whenas thoſe that are taught and admoniſhed, doe thus kicke and ſpurne at their teachers, and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they could, they would perſecute and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them euen vnto the death;<note place="margin">Petr. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr in <hi>2.</hi> ca. Rom.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that tho horſes and aſſes doe kicke thoſe that doe heale and cure their gaule backes, yet they neuer ceaſe curing them, till that they be full whole; much rather ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith he, muſt wee (though all the afflictions in the world bee laid vpon vs) indeuour to heale vp the vvounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:97"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 101.</hi> How high the calling of miniſters is: and how little fooliſh world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings reſpect them.</head>
               <p>BVt tell mee, my ſoule, why ſhould theſe gald-backe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thus reuile and ſcorne the ambaſſadours of Chriſt, as they daily doe; doe they thinke the miniſterie but a needleſſe thing, doe they eſteeme the medling with the ſecrets of God, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſoules, the ſhutting and opening of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to be but a triſte or matter of no value? they value them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in their vnequall ballance, they put them in the lighteſt ſcale; their moſt deformedſt ſonnes, and thoſe of the ſhallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt
<pb facs="tcp:3397:98"/>diſpenſers of the Lords will, the leaneſt beaſt, the lighteſt ſheafe of wheat is for Gods Church, all is too good that God hath; which plainely ſhewes vvhat vaine and curious prayers they offer vnto him, but when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to viſit them with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that they are like to die, who then is ſo much in requeſt as the Preachers, they deſire to bee buried in the Church, and withall to haue a Sermon too, though before in their life daies, they liued euen as Atheiſts, they would not ſo much as once lift a legge ouer the Church ſtile, to know their dutie, either towards God or man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:98"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 102.</hi> A meditation on Chriſt, who is the way, the trueth, and the life.</head>
               <p>O Sweet Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iobn.</hi> 14.6.</note> O thou the redeemer of mankinde, O thou who art the way, the trueth, and the life, the way in doctrine, precept and examples, the truth in promiſes, for thou Lord haſt performed thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to a thouſand gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and thou art the life in reward; I pray thee by this thine vnſpeakeable charity, wherwith thou vouchſafeſt to imploy thy ſelfe wholly for our ſaluation, ſuffer me neuer to wander from thee who art the way, neyther euer to diſtruſt in thy promiſes, who art the trueth, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt whatſoeuer thou doſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:99"/>neither to relie on any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, becauſe thou art e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, then which there is nothing more to be deſired, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen nor in earth; grant this I beſeech thee, O thou deare ſonne of God, to whom be praiſe and glorie for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 103.</hi> How impatient men are in endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring croſſes.</head>
               <p>JT is a ſtrange thing to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how impatiently the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſuffer puniſhments, &amp; how diſcontentedly the godly indure croſſes, wheras the ſin of both is the cauſe of both their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But if the wicked doe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcape in this life vnpuniſhed, it maketh much for the comfort
<pb facs="tcp:3397:99"/>of the Godly, in that the Lord giueth the raines, that they may gallop vnto their owne confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; God verie ſeldome or neuer giues the bridle vnto the Godly, but by fatherly chaſtiſements reſtraineth and amendeth them. Yet ſuch is the corruption of the fleſh in both, that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly kicke againſt the pricke of the Lords correction: Fewe men haue imbraced content, few reioice or ſmile in troubles, and few tryumph in the weariſome Chariot of aduerſitie: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented are prepared to beare the yoake of any afflictions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, whatſoeuer may fall out vnto them: <hi>Phidias</hi> that skilfull caruer of Images, did not onely cut them out of Iuorie, but alſo of braſſe, marble,<note place="margin">Senecain Epiſt. <hi>86.</hi>
                  </note> out of any kinde of ſtone, nay, out of the baſeſt brickleft mettall that was
<pb facs="tcp:3397:100"/>brought vnto him: And the wiſe man will place content in euery little corner of his life, in riches, in pouerty, in health, in ſickneſſe, as well in bondage and ſlauerie, as in freedom: as proſperity can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not breede pride and preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in him, ſo likewiſe cannot aduerſitie make him deſpaire: But alas, in theſe latter daies, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience and diſcontent haue ſmothered vp many good and Godly mindes, one cryeth like the horſe, oh I would I were an oxe for I am ſpurred, oh I would I were an horſe for I am goaded; thus one houles in one corner, one complaines in another, one ſobs and ſighes, another grieues and groanes, one wrings and wreſts his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, another ſtorms, ſtares and fumes ſo that heere is no place free from complaints and bewaylings, we are all Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb facs="tcp:3397:100"/>in this onething, for that wee wiſh our bodies may liue without griefes &amp; diſeaſes, and our mindes void of all ſorrow and pertur bations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 104.</hi> Comforts for ſuch as are poore &amp; miſerable.</head>
               <p>FIrſt then, me thinkes I heare one crie, pouertie is grieuous vnto me; I am poore and naked alas I am cold and hungrie: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo? well, let mee deale with the firſt in the nature of a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, (which will beſt fitt and ſatisfie the deſires of all our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh, and ignorant Chriſtians) It is grieuous vnto thee? fie, fie, this one reproachfull word hath done much harme vnto innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pouertie, it cannot bee grieuous vnto it, all the fault lyeth in thy
<pb facs="tcp:3397:101"/>diſcontented minde,<note place="margin">Senec de Rome. vtri. uſ. ſortu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> thou broughteſt nothing into the world, and nothing ſhalt thou carrie out, and this is the ſtate and condition of euerie ſoule breathing on the face of the earth, what is it then prethee tell me that thou canſt chalenge? art thou poore? then art thou free from theeues, free from care in keeping of goods, and from ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in looſing them or depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from them, yea, and now ſhalt thou bee free from ſetting thine hand to any band for thy friend: for through ſuretiſhip ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> many men are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.1.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.18.</note> I warrant thee through this ſuretiſhip, if thou art poore though neuer ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, thou ſhalt neuer take harm, bee of good cheere, for through pouerty thou haſt eſcapt an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred more troubles. Art thou
<pb facs="tcp:3397:101"/>poore and in miſerie? complain not thy wants ſo inſtantly, God ſeeth thee vnfit for riches and apt to be ſhooled by pouertie;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1</note> All vnder the ſunne is vanitie, trouble and vexation of minde, what hath man to mourne for then, when as all that hee can looſe in this life, is fading, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and tranſitorie, nay, the world cannot take away any thing, for it giueth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, fame periſheth, wealth decaies, and this onely remaines behinde with vs, and it is our true and onely wealth too, that is our conſtancie in croſſes: if then thou wilt fight, reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the world, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in Chriſts battell, hee ſhall take thee for his true-hearted ſouldier, and dubbe thee Knight for thy conſtancy in conquering, for thy famous victories, let nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3397:102"/>ioy nor griefe ouercome thee,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 6.15.16. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.4</note> for better were it not to be then to be a bondſlaue vnto paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Art thou poore? yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, thinke with thy ſelfe that the humble thoughts that ſmoke from thy poore cottage, are as ſweet a ſacrifide vnto god, as the vaine-glorious perfumes in the Pallace of a Prince? Art thou poore? ſo was <hi>Bias,</hi> but <hi>Bias</hi> was wiſe, be thou alſo wiſe with him, and art thou hard fauoured with <hi>Bias,</hi> be thou alſo learned with him, ſo then they that look vpon thee will deceiue themſelues, both in thy riches and alſo in thy beautie, truely it is the greateſt beautie to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with learning, and greateſt wealth, to be inriched with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, a poore man vertuous is as far beyond a rich man vicious as the ſoule is beyond the body
<pb facs="tcp:3397:102"/>it is better to be a man without money, then to be money with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a man, wherefore if aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie approacheth learn wiſdom: if thy troubles bee ſmall beare them, becauſe they bee eaſie to be borne, but if they be great &amp; grieuous beare with them alſo, for in ſo dooing, thy glorie ſhall be the greater, nay, both in bearing them, and alſo bearing with them, it is thy duetie, and and ſo ſhalt thou purchaſe the reward of obedience; laſtly if thou canſt not haue what thou wouldeſt, thou muſt be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with what thou canſt gette; to will much is follie, where ability wanteth, and to deſire nothing is content, which deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſeth all things. If thou haſt neither land nor liuing, labour diligently, and eate thy bread in the ſweat of thy browes, ſo God
<pb facs="tcp:3397:103"/>commanded and appointed thy father <hi>Adam</hi> to doe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.</note> and the riches that proceed heere-hence are ſweeteſt, &amp; the bleſſing beſt of all, and tell and thoſe my ſoule, what they muſt truſt too, that haue hands?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 105.</hi> For ſuch as are viſited with ſickneſſe.</head>
               <p>ANother crieth, I am horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly puniſhed with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, art thou ſo? perſwade thy ſelfe that thou ſhalt haue caſe anon; wherefore did God create Phyſitions, ſaue onely to helpe the ſicke; what if thou art ſick now, perſwade thy ſelfe that ſickeneſſe and diſeaſes cannot laſt long, for eyther thou
<pb facs="tcp:3397:103"/>wilt leaue them, or elſe they will leaue thee, we cannot be at one ſtay; it maketh no matter how ill thy budy be, ſo that thy ſoule be ſound, indeed if the inward man haue a paine in his head, wherby he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not lay him downe in peace and take his reſt, the contagion then ſurly is much to be feared;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8</note> thinke not that bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſickneſſe is any croſſe at all, it is rather a propertie, who then may auoid it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 106.</hi> For ſuch as are griened with old age.</head>
               <p>THe third crieth old age is crept vpon mee, I am filled with griefes and aches, alas my body is weake, thereby mine hands ſhake, mine eyes dazell
<pb facs="tcp:3397:104"/>my feet tremble; ſo that I am wearie of my life, I would to God I wer a yard vnder grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or elſe I would I were as luſtie as euer I was, ah ſinfull wiſh, I ſee now that thou delighteſt in naught, but in ſporting and toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vanities &amp; vain pleaſure: if Gods ſpirit did dwell in thee, thou wouldeſt not ſo earneſtlie complaine, but giue God praiſe and thanks for thy long life, and reioyce at thy gray head, which deſerues much honour:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieuit.</hi> 19.</note> this is that age which the Lord hath promiſed vnto all them that loue him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.</note> and keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that their daies ſhall be long in the land, that they ſhall liue many yeares. Nay, this is that age which euerie man defireth: and tell mee, didſt not thou thy ſelfe deſire to ſee it when thou
<pb facs="tcp:3397:104"/>waſt young, thinke then that thou art happie now, for that thou haſt thy wiſh; this alſo is no croſſe, onely a propertie,<note place="margin">Porphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, p op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra de Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nect.</note> &amp; onely belonging vnto man, but not vnto euerie man. In this age there is no ſwilling, no ſwearing no ſwaggering, no quaffing nor ſurfeiting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 107.</hi> For ſuch as are diſcontented for that they muſt leaue the world.</head>
               <p>ANd now who is hee that will not complaine when he muſt die, and howle and cry when he muſt leaue this world; who will ſay from his heart I haue liued a great while? this then is the part of an vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, who is not contented with the time hee hath liued;
<pb facs="tcp:3397:105"/>Grieue not becauſe thou muſt dy, that thou muſt leaue thy wife and children, thy lands and lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and all things elſe behinde thee, ſay not thou woe is mee, woe is mee that I muſt die: and muſt thou ſo,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 12</note> what then? It is the nature of a man to die, it is no puniſhment, when thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt firſt into the world it was vpon this condition, that thou ſhouideſt once goe out againe, this life is but peregrination, for when thou haſt walked vnto the end of thy iourney, thou muſt then returne backe, nay it is the part of a foole and a daſtard to feare that which by no meanes can bee auoided, many are gone before thee, and many ſhall goe after thee, and thou muſt knowe that thy life is not thine owne, thnu art onely <hi>vita commodatus</hi> and not <hi>donatus,</hi> thy life is onely
<pb facs="tcp:3397:105"/>lent vnto thee, thou haſt not a leaſe thereof, thou art but a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at will. Grieue not at the remembrance of death, for death it ſelfe cannot be greeuous ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is but once, it bringeth all happineſſe with it, and to the godly it is a verie great aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, But muſt thou die indeede? if Godly then be glad, if wicked repent, no man I trow wil ſpeak againſt death, ſaue he who hath a guiltie conſcience; death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed makes this man tremble &amp; quake, but thou ſhalt hardly ſee an honeſt man vnwilling to die; Yet another diſc ontented bloud cries out, alas, what muſt I dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my youthfull daies, how ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh and how ignorant art thou? tell me, what is not a commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſweeteſt, when as it commeth vnexpected? nay, death doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as well appertaine to youth
<pb facs="tcp:3397:106"/>as vnto old age, the Lambs skin comes euen as ſoon to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket as the ſheeps. And it makes no matter how many yeres thou haſt to liue, but how many thou haſt liued, then if thou canſt liue no longer, that is thine old age; and this the ſtate and condition of all mankinde, euen to die at laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 108.</hi> For ſuch as are ſlandered.</head>
               <p>YEt another grieues becauſe hee is ſlaundered, ſo that me thinks there is neuer an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly minded man amongſt vs: art thou ſlaundered, if guiltleſſe reioyce, if guiltie amend; wilt thou grieue at ſlaunders, thou muſt knowe that no good man will ſlaunder thee; and wouldeſt thou bee praiſed of euill men, I
<pb facs="tcp:3397:106"/>tell thee to bee commended of them is as bad as to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for euill dooing; <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> did neuer any famous thing in all his life time,<note place="margin">Senec de odio &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</note> or yet what was praiſe-worthy, and yet did no man euer ſpeake againſt him, Oftentimes haue I ſaw cankers gnawing the greeneſt and freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt leaues, and oftentimes haue I likewiſe ſaw enuie pricking thoſe eſpecially that were god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and religious be thou then of good comfort, if <hi>Cicero,</hi> if <hi>Scipio</hi> if <hi>Cato,</hi> if <hi>Dauid,</hi> if <hi>Salomon,</hi> if <hi>Peter,</hi> if <hi>Paul,</hi> or if any of the Prophets or Apoſtles, if any good man ſhould ſpeake euill of thee, then hadſt thou ſome cauſe to grieue, but theſe as malitious vipers doe enuie thy proſperitie, no honeſt or vertuous man will backebite his neighbour, and we know that the veryeſt whore
<pb facs="tcp:3397:107"/>will crie whore firſt; they that are moſte vicious will ſooneſt ſpeake of other mens vices, of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deformities and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, there are alſo many dogs that barke often,<note place="margin">Senec. de Kemed. for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit.</note> not for any cauſe that they haue, but onelie for cuſtome ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 109.</hi> For ſuch as haue loſt their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</head>
               <p>YEt me thinkes I heare ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet ſighing for that he hath loſt his money, what if thy money be gone? now thou art in leſſe daunger, oh how happie were thou if thou hadſt loſt thy couetouſnes with it too, art ſure thou haſt loſt thy money? pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee tell me, how many, money hath loſt, truely thou hadſt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:3397:107"/>looſe it then to let it looſe thee, and now ſhalt thou bee more light in thy iourney and more ſafe at home.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 110.</hi> For ſuch as are lame and ill fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</head>
               <p>ANother is diſcontented, and cries, alas I am lame, I goe vppon crouches, I am crompt ſholdred, crooked &amp; deformed, I am of an vgly viſage and the like, ſo that the leaſt and lighteſt croſſe is burdenſome and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous vnto vs. Art thou defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? ſo was <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſo was graue and prudent <hi>Aeſope,</hi> and yet both of them in their age, the wiſeſt men that were, it is not the proper flature of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, its not the beard, the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uizing
<pb facs="tcp:3397:108"/>countenance, ſtately ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, new faſhions, new cuts, rings, Iewels, or yet any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ornament elſe that makes the man, and likewiſe on the contrarie, its not a platter face, maimed limmes, one legge, one arme, or yet a paire of bow-legs that hindereth his difinition: a man as he is a man doth not conſiſt of fleſh and bloud, but of minde and courage, of ſoule and ſpirit, we ſay ſuch a beaſt is a faire beaſt, but we ſay ſuch a man is a vertuous man, which vertue onely proceedeth from his minde, pray how doe we define a man? we doe not ſay a man is a liuing Creature ſet out with a large paire of hoſe, or the like; but wee rather define him thus:<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Homo est animal ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionale;</hi> a man is a liuing creature indued withreaſon; to
<pb facs="tcp:3397:108"/>conclude a man is a man, if hee hath but a ſocke on his head: What art thou lame indeed? be content thy crouch ſerueth as well to fight withall, as to leane on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 111.</hi> For ſuch as are baniſhed.</head>
               <p>SOme againe weepe by cauſe they are baniſhed, but let me aske them whether they haue not deſerued it: indeed, we ſay that fooles and children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly will eate their cake, and yet haue it too, if they could; but bee thou contented: its no croſſe at all, though thou think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it one; its law &amp; iuſtice, it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth wel thy deſert: what though thou art baniſhed out of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thou ſhalt dwel in another, thou canſt not bee baniſhed out of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:109"/>the world, oh I ſhal be baniſhed out of my countrie wherein I was borne: thou art deceiued, for <hi>Patria eſt vbicunque bene eſt,</hi> that is thy countrie, not that wherein thou waſt borne, but wherein thou canſt beſt liue; what is thy baniſhment? it is but a trauelling, and what noble ſpirit doth not deſire to trauaile and to ſee new faſhions, if thou art not baniſhed from the land of the liuing, thou haſt no cauſe to grieue; Oh but I ſhall then die in a ſtrange countrie, what then? thou ſhalt goe to heauen in a ſtrange land, as ſoone as in thy natiue countrie, for heauen (contrarie to the rules of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie,) is a centre and the earth a circumference, from which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the centre are drawne many lines, and though many aſcend vp one line, many byanother, yet
<pb facs="tcp:3397:109"/>at length all meet and reioyce in one and the ſame place; let not this thought vexe thee, for there is no earth ſtrange vnto a dead man; but yet alas it may be as I wander vp and downe, I ſhall dy by my ſelfe, and ſo I may lie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buried, what then? thou ſhalt feele neither colde nor heat, winde nor weather, nay, if thou dooſt reſpect that, it is warmer lying aboue ground where the ſunne ſhineth pleaſantly, then vnder the earth where is naught elſe but a colde crude and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh moyſture; and what if thou ſhalt lie vnburied? know that <hi>Coelo tegitur qui non habet vrnam</hi> hee that hath neuer a graue or coffin to ſhadow him, hath the whole heauens to couer him. What care I when I am once dead, whether fier conſumes me, wilde beaſts deuour me, the ſea
<pb facs="tcp:3397:110"/>drownes mee, or the earth rots me; ſurely I will neuer take thought for my body, had not I as good let the birds thoſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle prettie harmeleſſe creatures picke gently my bones, as to let thoſe filthy ſtinking maggots deuour them: burying was not inuented firſt for thoſe ſakes that die, but for thoſe that remaine aliue afterward, that ſo all the noyſome ſmels and ſtinking vapours ariſing from the dead carkaſſe,<note place="margin">Senee de Rem. for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit.</note> might bee kept from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 112.</hi> For ſuch as weepe for loſſe of Children.</head>
               <p>YEt crieth another I haue loſt my Children, Oh what will become of mee, alas how
<pb facs="tcp:3397:110"/>ſottiſh art thou, to grieue for mortalitie, is it a ſtrange mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſee thy Children die? ſurely its no matter to ſee the tree ſtand and the Apples fall; and no more ſtrange is it then to ſee the fruite of thy bodie diſeaſed, and thy ſelfe aliue; now ſhalt thou neuer heare worſe of them, and wilt thou mourne for that they bee in ioy? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye then thou dooſt not loue them, though thou ſeemeſt loath to leaue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 113.</hi> For ſuch as mourne becauſe they are in bondage.</head>
               <p>ANd laſtly another cries, I am a ſlaue, I am a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; doſt not know, <hi>Qui non didicit parere non poteſt impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare,</hi> hee that hath not learned
<pb facs="tcp:3397:111"/>to obey, can neuer gouerne or rule his houſhold well; thou needeſt not now to hoe (as wee ſay) for houſ-rent, ſeruants wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the like things which thy maiſter doth, if thou art not a ſlaue vnto old Sathan al is wel; But alas I haue not my belly ful, if thou haſt not, bee contented, for God puniſheth the glutton as much as he doth thee; if thou haſt ſtomacke and little vittailes, hee hath vittailes and little ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, if thou laboureſt for meat for thy ſtomacke, hee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth for ſtomacke for his meat; nay, the drunken to ſpot is as often thirſtie, as the drie trauailer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:111"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 114.</hi> An example of content in Dyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines the Cynicke.</head>
               <p>I Wonder greatly at the impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of this age, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer a fleabiting without rubbing and ſcratching, learne of the ſillie bird, who although ſhe be kept in a cloſe cage, bard from all liberties and pleaſures, minſt of her diet, yet ſings ſhee more melodious and ſweete, then ſhe that flies abroad, in the open ayre, no cloſe impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no thought can moleſt her: But we are ſullen in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, murmuring in croſſes, and powting in our ſweeteſt trobles, what though my lodging be in bulkes, porches, and tubs,<note place="margin">Vita Dyog.</note> what though my dyet bee almes, bee roots and hearbs, what though my drinke bee water, my riches
<pb facs="tcp:3397:112"/>pouertie: and mine honour, onely taunts and ſcoffs; yet ſhall theſe as yee terme them croſſes breed a diſcontentment in mee? no, no. I know my tub to bee more beautifull then <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> great pallace, neither would I change any iot of my eſtate for his, though hee if he were not <hi>Alexander</hi> would be <hi>Dyogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> yet I of I were not <hi>Dyogines,</hi> would not bee <hi>Alexander,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Alex.</note> for I thinke his ſo gorgeous an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation woefull: and what ſaith my ſoule vnto his ſo proud and ſumptuous a pallace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Alas.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="115" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 115.</hi> The end of affliction.</head>
               <p>IF a man liues contented with his affections, they ſcowre all filth from his ſoule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.15.</note> that eternall
<pb facs="tcp:3397:112"/>part, for through many troubles and afflictions he muſt enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of heauen, hee that hath croſſes muſt imbrace nay, coll and kiſſe them. And then what ſaith my ſoule, if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beares them patiently heare on earth, is obtained in heauen through euerie diſteaſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> His eaſe.</p>
               <p>And what throgh euery afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Sion.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="116" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 116</hi> How carefull God is in afflicting his Children.</head>
               <p>SVrely the loue of God is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding large towards man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13</note> in that he layeth no more afflictions on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then that they can eaſily beare, he is ſparing in curſing, but bountifull in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, hee giueth his wrath by
<pb facs="tcp:3397:113"/>weight, but his mercie without meaſure; Amongſt all men ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee vndoubtedly is bleſſed on the one ſide, whome no feare troubleth, no penſiuenes conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, no deſire of worldly wealth afflicteth, and to whome no croſſe can ſeeme intollerable, whereby he may be diſcouraged or deſpaire; and hee likewiſe is happie on the other ſide, whome no pleaſure can proudly puff vp, no delight can ſo mooue vnto mirth, and no promotion make him ſo vaine-glorious, whereby hee preſumes aboue others, or preferres himſelfe before them, for oftentimes haue I ſaw, and how often I know not the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hoyſted vp into the ſaddle, when as hee that rode before, hath now beene glad to lackie after. The riches that men ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in time may faile; friendes
<pb facs="tcp:3397:113"/>may proue vnkinde and vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, hope may deceiue, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent can neuer be conquered: the contented man kils aduerſity if it aſſault, dries vp teares if they flow, ſtayes wrath if it vrge, heales woundes if they feſter, and and laſtly wins heauen and heauenly ioyes, if it hold on vnto the end, and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> learned in what ſtate ſo euer hee was in,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11</note> therewith to be content.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="117" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 117.</hi> Comforts in generall for ſuch as are in afflictions.</head>
               <p>NOw leauing the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers reaſons, let vs ſee my ſoule how farre the Chriſtian reaſoning, can comfort vs in induring croſſes: ſurely their fruite is verie great; firſt then
<pb facs="tcp:3397:114"/>for by them through Chriſt, we purchaſe remiſſion of finnes, and reconciliation to God the father by them wee are exerciſed in Godlineſſe, and for ſuffering them wee ſhall haue our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, a reward of ineſtimable value, me thinkes then that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſhould not make mee diſpaire and greue, and ſeeing that Chriſt Ieſus our Captaine hath broke downe the hedge, before our eyes, I ſay let it not grieue vs now to follow after, all the ſaints of God, his Souldiers, all the Prophets and Martyrs, haue ſounded the bottome, and found the depth of all afflictions whatſoeuer, feare not then thy footing: God plaies the carefull cooke with all his children, he giues them ſharp Oliues to whet their ſtomakes, and breed their appetites, ſharp ſorrows, ſowre
<pb facs="tcp:3397:114"/>croſſes, bitter and briniſh trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, becauſe they ſhould come and taſte how ſweet, how good and gracious the Lord is, we are puniſhed in this world ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> to the end wee ſhould not be damned with the world, in the world to come: In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as a Nurſe that to weane her childe from the loue and liking of her milke, doth rubbe her tear with aloes, with wormewood or with the like bitter thing, ſo our mercifull father who would faine retire vs from the loue of the world, and worldly delights, vſeth to ſend tribulation vnto vs therein, to the intent wee may crie with the childe paw, pan vnto the world, to the end wee may ſhun and auoide its intiſing dugs. Againe we reade that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſtriking with his rod the hard rockes brought ſorth water,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.5, 6</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3397:115"/>and the rod of correction falling on the backe of ſtony-hearted ſinners, moſt commonly mollifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to contrition, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes bringeth forth a flood of teares to repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="118" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 118.</hi> On the ſame.</head>
               <p>THe ſtones that were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſerue for the glorious temple of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  </note> were beaten, were hewed and poliſhed with out, at the quarry ſide, for that no ſtroake of hammer might be heard within the temple, and <hi>Peter</hi> tels vs that the Godly are choſen ſtones, to bee placed in the ſpirituall building, of God in heauen, where there is no bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, no hewing, no ſorrow, no tribulation: ſurely then it is meet for vs here in this life, in the hard
<pb facs="tcp:3397:115"/>quarrie of this ſinfull world, to be cut and poliſhed, and made fit for that glorious temple; and with all wee ought to bee moſt glad when we are thus handled,<note place="margin">Pſalme. Amos <hi>4.1.</hi>
                  </note> for that it is a ſigne of our electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to that moſt glorious houſe of Gods eternall manſion. Oxen appointed for the ſlaughter are ſuffered to feed at their pleaſure, &amp; ſo are <hi>Dauids</hi> fat Buls of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan: trees that bring foorth no fruite, and are kept for the fier, are neuer beaten, and the ſicke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is paſt all hope of health is ſuffered by the Phiſitian to haue whatſoeuer hee luſteth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when as hee whoſe health is not deſpaired, cannot haue that liberty graunted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="119" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:116"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 119.</hi> We ought to reioice in troubles.</head>
               <p>MEthinks how neceſſary it is to knowe, that all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come from a diuine and iuſt hand, wherefore they cannot be euill or vnwholeſome, as many account them; Indeed croſſes are verie troubleſom vnto the weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe and frailtie of the fleſh, yet if thou wilt behold their effect thou haſt cauſe enough to bee merrie, to bee patient and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented therewith; The ſeafaring man, who althogh he be beaten moſt grieuouſly with ſtormes and toſt verie dangerouſly with bluſtering windes, yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the hauen ſmiles to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and cleareth vp his dull and heauy ſpirits, if he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioyceth in the middes of thoſe ſtormes beholding the hauen a recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle
<pb facs="tcp:3397:116"/>only for his wearyed body, thou rather mayeſt (I think) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, caſting thy eyes on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, a ſweet refreſhing ſhoare for thine afflicted ſoule Its a moſt baſe and crauoniſh part to grieue for the want of any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefit, what ſhall olde age make me ſigh, ſhal pouertie make me mourn, ſhal ſickeneſſe make me diſpaire, or ſhal death it ſelfe make me affraid, no, no, he truely is no man that in this life is not filled with miſeries, &amp; hee is no Chriſtian that cannot bear them, troubles are but flea-bitings, but alas wee vnskilfull worldlings, know not their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Tell me then my ſoule what that ſoule ſhall obteine in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which ſuffers croſſes patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here on earth, tell me my ſoule what ſhal there be caſt vpon her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="120" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:117"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 120</hi> The reward of ſuch as are patient in troubles.</head>
               <p>ANd what can bee a greater dignitie then to be cloathed with the brightneſſe of GOD, then to be indued with immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie? and what can be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace or an higher felicitie to any ſoule, then to ſee God face to face, for his face is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all beatitude, to ſee him that made both heauen and earth, to ſee him that made thy ſeife, to ſee him that redeemed thee, and glorified thee, for in ſeeing him thou ſhalt poſſeſſe him, in poſſeſſing him thou ſhalt loue him, in louing him, thou ſhalt praiſe him; for hee is the inheritance of his people, he is the poſſeſſion of their felicitie,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:117"/>their reward, their crowne of glorie, in him our ſoules, ſhall finde all wiſdome, all beautie, all riches, all delight, all goodneſſe whatſoeuer, whatſoeuer deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth loue or admiration or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pleaſure and contentation. Briefly, in this kingdome, there ſhall bee ioy without ſadneſſe, health without ſickneſſe, life without labour, light without darkenes, felicity without abate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, all goodneſſe without any euill; loe thus ſhal he be bleſſed that patiently indureth croſſes, troubles and afflictions, their youth floriſheth, and neuer wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth olde, life that knoweth no end, beautie that neuer fadeth, loue that neuer cooleth, health that neuer diminiſheth, ioy that neuer ceaſeth, a ſong of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that neuer endeth, there ſhal we ſing &amp; reioice for euer,
<pb facs="tcp:3397:118"/>happie are they,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.</note> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> that liue in thy houſe for they ſhall praiſe thee eternally, there ſhall we ſing vnto that bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God the Father, God the ſonne, and God the holy Ghoſt, we ſhall ſing and cry <hi>Aleiluia, Aleiluiah,</hi> world without end.</p>
               <p>Awake now my ſoule, rouſe vp thy ſelfe and ariſe, call to thy friends and companions, that wee may all goe together and heare the ſpirituall talke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and his poore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted members; make haſt my ſoule, for I heare the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpeeches of my redeemer, ſounding in my eares alreadie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="121" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:118"/>
               <head>A DIALOGVE BETWEENE CHRIST and his Church afflicted, by <hi>which wee may eaſily ſee, what</hi> Chriſt doth require of thoſe, that ſuffer perſecution, for his name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake: and how they ought to behaue themſelues in afflictions.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſtus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N mee yee ſhall haue peace,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.33.</note> in the world ye ſhal haue affliction, but bee of good comfort, I haue ouercome the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſia afflicta.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord increaſe our faith.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 17.5.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Come vnto me all ye that are wearie and laden,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28</note> and I will eaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter to whom ſhall we goe to els?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.68.</note> thou haſt the words of eternall life.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:119"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>Follow me.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.19</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter I will follow thee whitherſoeuer thou goeſt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.19</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>I am the good Shepheard<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.11</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>We were as the good ſheep going aſtray,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25</note> but are now returned to the Shepheard and biſhop of our ſoules.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>I am the light of the world<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.12.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>Lord lighten my eyes, leaſt they behold death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>I am the way.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>Shew vs the way of thy truth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.33</note> teach mee O Lord the way of thy ſtatutes, and I will keepe it vnto the end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr:</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſed are ye that weep now.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 6.21.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord ſhall wipe clean away all teares from our eyes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſed are yee when men hate you.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 6.22.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>If I ſhould pleaſe men I were not the ſeruant of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſed are the pure in<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3397:119"/>heart for they ſhall ſee God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Create in me a new heart O Lord.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſalme</hi> 50.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt,</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſed are they which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10.</note> for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ:</speaker>
                  <p>I ſuffer all thinges for the elects ſake.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ti.</hi> 2.10.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>Lay vp treaſures for your ſelues in heauen.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.20.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl.</speaker>
                  <p>Our conuerſation is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>Wo be to you when all men ſpeake well of you.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 6.26.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee ought rather to obey God then men.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 5.20</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt:</speaker>
                  <p>Reioice and be glad, for great is your reward in heauen.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl:</speaker>
                  <p>There is laid vp for mee the crown of righteouſnes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8</note> which the Lord ſhall giue me at that day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>My ſheepe heare my voice,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.27</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl:</speaker>
                  <p>If an angel of heauen preach vnto vs any other gospell,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8</note> let him be accurſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:120"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I came not to cal the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous but ſinners to repentance.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a true ſaving,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</note> This is a true ſaving, and by all means worthy to be receiued that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners, of whome I am the chiefe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If any man will follow me,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24</note> let him forſake himſelfe, and take vp his Croſſe and follow me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I am able to do all things through Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13</note> which ſtrengthneth me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>He that beleeueth in mee ſhall neuer die.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.26</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue that thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God.<note place="margin">Iohn ib.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer ſhall humble himſelfe as a little childe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 18 4.</note> the ſame is the greateſt in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee are vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10</note> wee haue done but that
<pb facs="tcp:3397:120"/>which was our duetie to doe.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.32</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>My father giueth you the true bread from heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord euermore giue vs this bread.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 6.34.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer drinketh of the water that I ſhall giue him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.14</note> ſhall neuer be more a thirſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, giue me of that water that I may not thirſt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.15</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Feare not my little flocke.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lord in thee haue I truſted, let me neuer bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray for them that hurt you and perſecute you.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord lay not this ſinne to their charge.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 7 60</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee that loueth father or Mother more then hee loueth me,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.37</note> is not worthy of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>When my Father and my Mother forſooke me,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.10</note> thou Lord tookeſt me vp.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:121"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I came not to ſend peace but the ſword.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.34</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eceleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſhal ſeperate vs from the loue of Chriſt?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35</note> ſhall tribulation or anguiſh, or perſecution, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſword? &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye ſhall weepe and mourn but your ſorrow ſhall be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioy.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.20</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I account that the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent life are not worthy of the glorie,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18</note> that ſhall bee ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Where I am,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 12.26</note> there ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo my ſeruant be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I deſire to bee looſed,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</note> and to be with Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee that loueth his life ſhall looſe it,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.25</note> and hee that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his life in this world ſhall keepe it vnto life eternall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>For thy ſake are we kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all day long,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36</note> we are counted as
<pb facs="tcp:3397:121"/>for the ſlaughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If the world hate you,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.18</note> yee knowe, that it hated me before it hated you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>If God be ou our ſide who can be againſt vs?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 31.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſeruant is not greater then the Maſter.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 15 20</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Chriſt hath ſuffered for vs leauing vs an example that wee ſhould followe his ſteps.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>In my fathers houſe are many dwelling places.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.2.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccleſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee know,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor</hi> 5.1</note> that if our earthly houſe of this tabernacle be deſtroyed, wee haue a building giuen of God, an houſe not made with handes, but eternall in the heauens.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>GOD ſent not his ſonne into the world,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17</note> that hee ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the world, but that the world through him might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:122"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl.</speaker>
                  <p>Let vs therefore goe bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto the throne of grace,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14.</note> that we may receiue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in time of need.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>He that beleeueth in the ſoune ſhall not be condemned.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh</hi> 3.18.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> which are in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chri.</speaker>
                  <p>All the haires of your head are numbred.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 10 30</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord knoweth who are his.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye beleeue in God,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.1.</note> beleeue alſo in me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eccl.</speaker>
                  <p>We beleeue &amp; know that thou art the Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.69.</note> the ſonne of the liuing God.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS Dialog.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="122" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:122"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 122.</hi> The true felicitie of this life and the falſe.</head>
               <p>GOD hath giuen vs a true felicitie in this life, a true practick I meane, which is the continuall meditation on the Lawes of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1.2.</note> though not a diuine and theorick which is els where; yet ſome men thinke pleaſure with ſwiniſh <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> ſome thinke honour, with vaine glorious <hi>Periander,</hi> and ſome thinke riches with couetous <hi>Midas;</hi> But how can this bee? when as gold and ſiluer are but the very excrements of nature, and found in the moſt barren and barbarous places of the earth; they cannot eaſe the grief of the bodie, much leſſe then of
<pb facs="tcp:3397:123"/>minde: how againe can honour be the felicitie of this life being but a vapour ſoone vaniſhing, onely the breath of ſome mens mouthes?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 7</note> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> did not regard it when hee ſaid vnto rottenneſſe, thou art my father, vnto duſt and wormes, yee are my ſiſters and my mother. If any one then will bragge of the fame and renown of his aunceſters, let him looke with holy <hi>Iob</hi> into their graues, and there hee ſhall ſee all honor and promotion of this life to be turned into a little loathſome ſtinking earth; And how then, beaſtlie Epicure, can pleaſure be the felicitie, of this life? when as it killeth the ſoule, poyſoneth the bodie, when as it is naught elſe, but ſcum of venerie, and a iakes receptable for all filth and beaſtlineſſe, and then againe ſhould dogges bee in as good
<pb facs="tcp:3397:123"/>eſtate as man, if pleaſure ſhould bee the happineſſe of this life, nay, now in fine tell me my ſoule what is was, that brought on each wicked one of Iſraell, the Lords heauie wrath and ſore diſpleaſure?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> His pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And tell mee againe, what ſpace of time may caſt downe, all the flouriſhing robes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, and vtterly deface the beautie of honour?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> One houre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="123" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:124"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 123.</hi> The world is vnconſtant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man muſt be conſtant.</head>
               <p>THe world is full of change and alteration, here grieſes hang ouer pleaſures, here warre ariſeth in the middeſt of peace, here ſecuritie is turned into ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den feare, here a friend is ſoone become an enemie, and here all our ſommers paſtimes are ſoone changed into winters threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thunderclaps; the ſommer turneth into winter, the day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to night, youth into age, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie into aduerſitie, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures into ſorrowes, ſo that for riches we exchange pouertie, for health ſickneſſe, and for honour and renowne, contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; nay in fine, this life is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb facs="tcp:3397:124"/>in nothing but in incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, it is conſtant in nothing, but that it is vnconſtant in all things; Seeing then that this life is thus vnconſtant and ful of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, mans heart muſt be filled with content, hee muſt learne with <hi>Paul</hi> to bee content with the ſtate whereto hee is called,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil</hi> 4.11.</note> without grudging. This godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent depending on the Lords will, is the onely ſluice that ſtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth and ſtoppeth all the raging floods of misfortune; we know this, that there is no part of a mans life ſo cloſe and ſecure, but that the feare of death may creepe in, that there is no mans life ſo fortified about with peace and happineſſe, but that griefe now and then may ſhake and terrifie him, whereſoeuer a man hides himſelfe calamitie will ſeeke him out, and ſtill attend
<pb facs="tcp:3397:125"/>on him; here are many external and outward euils, which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and tempt vs vnto lewdnes here are alſo many inward and ſecret complaints of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, many griefes, many cares, which in time wil exciccate and conſume the body, yet a ioyfull and contented ſoule, like of ſound &amp; well headed waſter puts them off all without any foile or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh at all; ſuch a cauellering ſpirit or reſolute vnder Chriſts banner, cares not thogh ſtrength be ſubiect to weakenes, riches to pouertie, health to ſickeneſſe, fame to diſgrace, or life to death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="124" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:125"/>
               <head>SECT. 124. <hi>The tokens of a wiſe man, and contented.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very wiſeman, hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually this thought in his heart, he thinketh that he fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth death, when as hee doth but onely heare thereof; hee ſuppoſeth that he ſmarteth with his brothers wants, when as hee doth but onely ſee them, hee doth as wel and as willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the worlds croſſes and calamities, as its ioyes and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities; hee deſpiſeth riches as well preſent as loſt or abſent, or thoſe which hee knowes hee ſhall neuer enioy, he neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth at their preſence, nor yet mourneth for their abſence; hee thinketh Gods bleſſing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3397:126"/>going away nor yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; hee perſwades himſelfe that all the earth is his, and that his is for all men, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee hath, hee doth neither miſerably keep nor yet prodigal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpend it, hee conceiueth this in his minde, that the friendſhip and ſocietie of men muſt bee as the ſtones in an ouen, one muſt ſtrengthen and vphold another; Theſe are the ſignes of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented ſoule,<note place="margin">Sence. Epi. <hi>96.</hi>
                  </note> thus to liue peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, and tell this to all men my ſoule, tell them what will driue away all calamitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Amitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="125" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:3397:126"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 125.</hi> The praiſe of content.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rotherly loue and content in this hard iron age, is the onely ſalue for all diſeaſes. I am weake, but therewith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, why then am I ſtronge, but not contented mith my ſtrength, then am I weake, I am ignorant, yet contented with the portion of wiſedome that God hath giuen mee, then am I wiſe, I am wiſe, yet would I faine know, <hi>Quod ſupra me eſt,</hi> that which is aboue my capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for to know, then am I foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, I am a foole: I am poore, yet contented therewith, why then am I rich, I haue abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, yet craue I more, then am I poore: Content to the
<pb facs="tcp:3397:127"/>weake and feeble is ſtrength, to the ſimple wiſdome, to the poore riches, to the ſlaundered praiſe, to the ſicke health, to the aged, youth; to the afflicted comfort: nay what is it not? Its all in all. And now my ſoule, what ſhall I be gone? ſhall I bid thee farewell, and heere make an end with the worlds diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Yes, content.</p>
               <p>I had thought to haue made my race ſomewhat longer, but ſeeing it is thy will I ſhould end here, here then will I place my fartheſt poſt: good <hi>Eccho</hi> I ſay farewell, farewell, vntill wee talke againe, which God-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſhall not bee long firſt, if ſo bee that theſe our firſt buds that now ſpring, be not cropt or blited by ſome enuious brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing blaſt; which muſt hang on
<pb facs="tcp:3397:127"/>the good pleaſure of God, and onely on his will depend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> End.</p>
               <p>Ile end, and now farewel my ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccho.</hi> Here it.</p>
               <p>Here yet, and yet too, you will haue the laſt I ſee, but yet withall, I pray, let mee alſo bid all thoſe farewell,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3.</note> that are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the baſe humours of this age, ſuch as cannot well brooke or digeſt the lewd and filthie conditions of theſe latter times. So now once againe, my ſoule, I caſt you on him that made you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecch.</hi> Adieu.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
